Heat. Heat.
[music]
>> [music]
>> Heat. Heat.
[music]
>> Hello everybody. Good evening and good
day. I hope you're all doing great and
welcome to the Ask a Bidget show, the
latest episode. I hope you're doing
great. So, let us see. Uh, so today is
going to be a super chat live stream. I
will take questions about essentially
any topic. Ask me anything you want.
I'll try my best to answer your
questions. Before we get into that, let
me see who all is there on the live
chat. I can see Abhinav Mishra, Animesh,
Paratia, Biju, Sika, animals from Forlaf
from Mumbai, Chat DSP, Abhinav Capil,
Mahita Bushetti, Aayush Singh, Abin
again, Critical Thinker, Ketanya Manuja,
Geopolitical Dubai from Indor, Ashoto
Pande, Real Vladimir Putin, Meat
Mystery, Swami0709,
Animals from Laugh, Animals for Laugh
from Mumbai. Once again uh Raika Humbli
Jashi Ram Adwit Ashwani injured soccer
player is here from snowy Richmond Hill
in Ontario Canada. Good to have you sir.
Good morning
Ashi once again Ashwani King
Uti is here from Tulus of France.
Madame satellite is here. Uh, Suchin
Yadav, critical thinker once again. Who
else do we have? Let us see. Let us see
once again. Uh, Abisha once again.
I suppose that's about it. Or am I not
getting the chat the live chats?
Okay. So, we have everyone over here and
let us now take some questions.
What questions do we have? Let's get
going. First of all, Bascar is a new
member. Thank you very much, sir, for
becoming a new member. I really
appreciate that everybody welcome Baskar
to membership of the channel. Thank you
very much. Minimalist Maverick says 2025
Putin Modi summit latent activities
accomplished.
Okay. So we had we've had the recent uh
visit of Mr. Vladimir Putin to India and
I think it concluded yesterday. So it
was a two-day trip. So what's been the
outcome of this uh India Russia summit?
Mr. Putin came to India with a large
number of officials and there were
multiple events that he participated in
in New Delhi and he obviously met with
the prime minister, Prime Minister Modi.
Uh what's been the major activities that
happened? What have been the outcomes of
this summit? I think we are still
examining what the outcomes of the
summit have been. Some commentators have
said that the summit the the trip of Mr.
Putin the visit was maybe a little long
on symbolism and a little short on
outcomes. Uh I don't necessarily agree
with that. It's a very important uh
event that's happened geopolitically. Uh
it reinforces uh the closeness between
India and Russia. Uh obviously we
haven't seen any major announcements of
any major uh let's say military deals.
For example, people were speculating
maybe the Sukoy 57 deal will be
announced. That's not happened. Maybe
some kind of deal about the S400 will be
announced or S500. That's not happened.
But maybe that's not how the government
of India works. Maybe it's not like you
know see when someone like Trump visits
a place he wants to go back with a with
a with a set of accomplishments. I got
this this this done and he wants to you
know tell his people I got these things
done. I got this much money for the
United States. Um if some other
country's leader comes to India or goes
anywhere else, they also want to go back
with a set of things that they got done.
I think when it comes to India and
Russia, it's a very old relationship.
It's not like we had getting to know
each other. So we need to get certain
things done so that we feel that there's
been progress. There have there would
have been talks M between Mr. Modi and
Mr. Putin. They would have discussed all
the important bilateral issues. they
would have discussed what's happening
globally visav the United States visav
the European Union visa with the Ukraine
war vav China and many other things and
they would have uh you know got to
understand each other's perspectives
better obviously they would have been
even before the meeting they would have
been in communication on a regular basis
and they would know where where the two
two nations stand but it's important
that the two leaders connect and spend
time with each
And there have been
certain outcomes that have come out of
the visit so far that we can see. First
of all, there was the launch of the RT
India um
news network. So we have Russia today RT
which is well known. It's a it's
Russia's you could say global
mouthpiece. It's uh it operates in
English. It operates in Russian. Now
it's going to operate from India as
well. India specific office. So that's a
significant achieve significant uh
achievement or step forward. It shows
that see
it it shows that there is significant
closeness between the two nations. There
I think there was an announcement of
further India Russia nuclear cooperation
which is also pretty interesting. Uh
what are what the parameters of the
cooperation are going to be. Uh we'll
have to see. There's been uh
announcements about
more integrated India Russia defense
cooperation research and R&D is going to
happen. Joint development will happen
etc. What the details are we still have
to see. But there's been multiple you
know there's been progress on multiple
fronts. So I think we still have to see
what the outcomes of this visit are
going to be. But it's clear that India
has signaled to the world that Russia is
not isolated. India and Russia have a
very robust, very friendly, very warm
relationship. Prime Minister Modi made
it a point to go to the airport and
receive Mr. Putin, which is something he
rarely does for anybody anybody else.
Um,
and so I think it's it's still early
days to see to to to
kind of judge what the outcomes of this
uh trip to India by Mr. Putin have been,
but overall it's been very positive. So,
we'll uh keep an eye on what's going on.
Minimalist Maverick says why doesn't
Indian government make Iran our ally for
India Russia trade route? Why doesn't
India make Iran our ally? So we have a
good relationship with Iran. We don't
have any official allies. Even Russia
isn't officially our ally. We don't have
any official alliance or any official
treaty of alliance between India and
Russia. U but we have excellent
relations with Russia. For all intents
and purposes, Russia and India are
allies.
Even though they may not not officially
be allies, but for all intents and
purposes, we are. Now, when it comes to
Iran, India and Iran have a very good
relationship.
It's not a bad relationship. We are not
on bad terms with each other. And from
India's perspective, it it will be
beneficial for us if the current
government in Iran continues. We don't
want a fall of the current government in
in Iran and the the bringing about of a
democratic Iran or or any such thing
because the last time there was a there
was a non
there was a different kind of
government. It was pro- US proch
proakistan and anti-India. We don't want
that. Uh so we already have a very good
relationship with Iran. We have the
Chabahar port uh agreement. We operate a
certain amount of the certain certain uh
aspects of the Chabahar port. India and
Iran are cooperating in visav
Afghanistan. Uh India and Iran are also
cooperating vizav Armenia Azarbaijan
that situation. We have um various uh
various things that we are cooperating
on. So you could say that India and Iran
are kind of you know de facto allies in
certain matters. Obviously, there's
going to be points of friction like you
have with any any friendly nation.
There's going to be some points of
friction. We have points of friction.
Look,
Russia and China are said to be great
allies and great friends, right? Isn't
that true? But doesn't Russia sell all
kinds of frighteningly dangerous
military equipment to India which China
will not like? Yeah. And still their
relationship is pretty strong
nevertheless. So that's how it is. So
overall we don't have to officially put
a title of ally on somebody. Our
relationship itself is what matters not
the title we put on it. See
we in India are big fans of titles and
and and
symbols etc.
And we want it to be officially
declared. You are my best friend. You
are my ally. We are going to be allies.
You don't have to officially declare
anything.
Keep the relationship strong. Make it
stronger and keep it going that way
without going to the rooftops and
shouting from the rooftops with drums
and trumpets and everything. Then you
know we are allies. Just keep it quiet.
We already have a very good relationship
with Iran and that should continue.
Right. Okay. Baskar Bandit says,
"Namaste. Hope your health is better
better now. Last weekend I wasn't very
well, right? I was sneezing and
whatnot." Yeah. It's I think it's it was
some kind of virus or something. I'm
getting over it. I think my voice is
still affected. I think yesterday my
voice wasn't great. I think and probably
today it's better. So overall u on the
right track. Sure. Uh so for Mr. Modi
breaking from Mr. Modi breaking protocol
to receive Mr. Putin into Western
politicians melting down on social
media. What's your take on this historic
visit of sorts? What's my take? Um like
I just explained it's been a good visit.
uh in India and Russia we usually have
an annual summit and that's kind of been
disrupted since 2022 after the Russian
special military operation in Ukraine
began but it's good that uh this has
been resumed now so prime minister Modi
and Mr. Bhin have met face to face in
the same room for an extended period of
time Mr. Putin has been received here
and uh he has participated in various
events in India and obviously there
would have been uh long and intense
discussions between the two leaders and
the two sides which is obviously very
important for a good relationship to to
continue.
Uh as far as the outcomes are concerned
we don't have very robust specific you
know outcomes that can be listed in
bullet points but overall that doesn't
really matter. What matters is that the
two leaders meet and the countries
continue to uh cooperate with each other
and strengthen the relationship. There's
going to be some aspects of civil
nuclear uh cooperation. There's going to
be defense joint production and uh R&D
ata all that stuff.
As as some of you may know, India is
leasing
a Russian nuclear submarine.
Well, that itself should tell you how
strong the two the relationship between
the two nations is.
I mean which nation is going to lease a
nuclear submarine to you? A nuclear
submarine is the most coveted thing you
know oceangoing vessel apart from an
aircraft carrier. And today nobody cares
about aircraft carriers anymore because
the age of the aircraft carrier isn't
that is kind of gone. Today the most
dangerous
asset you can have in the oceans is the
submarine especially nuclear submarines
in Russia and India. the the the amount
of trust is such that Russia leases
nuclear submarines to India on 10-year
leases. Obviously, we pay them for that
as we should and that's how it is. So,
overall, it's been great. This visit
shows it tells the world that Russia is
not isolated by any means whatsoever.
Russia has a powerful and very important
friend in India. Russia is able to
counterbalance its relationship visa
with China with its relationship with
India.
India is no longer one of those little
nations that doesn't matter anymore.
India is a very consequential nation
today and the the consequentiality of
India is increasing every year. Uh so
that's why there's going to be these
meltdowns. I I myself you know these
days I don't tweet a lot on Twitter but
I do observe from time to time what's
happening and I saw saw plenty of
meltdowns from various people in Germany
and whatnot. Uh using all kinds of
colorful language about India etc. Well,
there there was fun to watch. It's it's
good to see these meltdowns. Yeah.
Because things are not going the way
they would like things to go. They would
like India to remain under their thumb.
They would like India to tow
their line and India is not doing that.
India is acting like a strong powerful
nation. Strong powerful sovereign nation
should. And that's what irks them so
much. The Urswile white masters. They no
longer consider Russians to be white. Do
you know that Russians are either?
They're not white people. Well, funny.
Uh anyhow, so the way I see it, it's
been a great visit and whatever the
outcomes,
takeaways, etc. are going to be from
this visit will be apparent over time,
over a period of time, not immediately.
And that's good.
Okay. Gajati Dave says, "Were the
Gajpati kings descendants of Sriam?" I
have no idea sir. I don't know.
Sorry, I am not aware of this.
Basar Bandit says the alleged
intentional disruption of certain
airline
Indigo.
Yes. Uh during uh Mr. Putin's visit to
India is raising eyebrows. What could
one hope to achieve with this act?
Domestic distraction, negative optics,
or is there more to the story? Indigo
needs to be taken to task by the
government of India. what they have done
is unacceptable. It's not like there was
a sudden lastm minute change of rules by
the government of India which forced
Indigo to cancel flights.
The government notification about the
rules the revised rules was announced
like 18 months ago or something more
than a year ago. So Indigo had plenty of
time to plan for this but they did not.
They they chose to arm twist the
government of India and the government
of India
acts in a certain way. It doesn't do
anything in a hurry. So they rolled back
the rules and they allowed Indigo to go
ahead with things. Indigo has caused
tremendous chaos in the country but
there are going to be consequences for
the for Indigo
because of what they've done. It'll
happen in time. What needs to be done is
Indigo needs to be brought to task for
this incredibly damaging disruption to
the Indian uh airline industry.
Indigo used to be India's best budget
airline
until about I don't know 2018 2019 very
professional always on time they would
charge for everything that's fine that's
okay it's a budget airline they'll
charge for everything they'll charge for
glass of whatever they'll charge for a
piece of bread they'll charge for each
seat will have a certain charge and if
you don't buy a buy a purchase seat then
they may not give you you know possibly
potentially a seat in the flight maybe
it's over booked
whatever, but it was on time. When you
get down and you stand in line for the
baggage, the baggage would come within a
few minutes. Today, Indigo is terrible.
Today, it's terrible compared to what it
was 2018, 2019. It's terrible.
And what they have done is is it should
be the straw that breaks the camel's
back. They have a foreign CEO
and uh overall it's terrible. And they
did this exactly when Mr. Putin came to
India. Right? So the government needs to
look into all these aspects and Indigon
must be held accountable and they must
be
taken to task for what's happened.
The problem is that it's become this
huge monopolistic airline.
Everybody by default books Indigo
because they are on time. Usual these
days they're not even on time. These
days Indigo is never on time and they
will always blame traffic congestion
this that whatever. Yeah.
But the these days they are never on
time and when you land I mean when you
land it it takes God knows how much time
for the for the for the luggage luggage
to come. Used to be very quick. So it's
never a good experience anymore
traveling by Indigo. I think it's a
better it used to be a better experience
traveling by Vistara and now it may even
be a better experience traveling by Air
India or maybe I've not not tried AASA
so far and I used to avoid SpiceJet.
Maybe I should try it one more time and
see how SpiceJet is today. Has it
improved because SpiceJet used to be the
worst.
Uh anyhow I'm going into other topics
here but I think Indigo needs to be
taken to task for this. What the
government should do the government
should decide. I am nobody to give them
recommendations. Do this, do that, break
their airline into three three different
companies or whatever. I'm not going to
recommend any of those things. The
government needs to hold the right
people accountable and Indigo must pray
must pay
the price
for what they've done. What they've done
is nothing short of criminal actually.
Yeah. So, what are they trying to
achieve? I don't know. Obviously
it's it's caused terribly negative
optics for India. It's caused terrible
disruptions at the time when Mr. Putin
visited India. I was very lucky. I mean
the day this nonsense happened I was in
Delhi and I was I was supposed to take a
flight out of Delhi and I was thankfully
booked on an AirIndia flight and I saw
firsthand the chaos at Delhi airport.
I mean the amount of the amount of
damage they've done to people's lives
and to the overall airline sector is
terrible. They need to be held
accountable and they need to be brought
to task for this. I hope the government
will do this
in the right manner that that the
government would choose. Okay. Basar Bit
says China seemingly bolstering western
front in Tibet while instability within
temporary nation seems high after Iran
Khan demise rumors. If two fronts open
up at the same time, how do we tackle
it?
We should always be prepared for a two
and a half or three-f frontont war. We
have East Pakistan and West Pakistan.
Now both are US was
China. See, China, you can never trust
China. Okay? China is not going to be
our friend. China is not going to be
India's friend. As long as China is an
occ is is occupying Tibet, India and
China, the relationship can never be
normal.
Two large powerful nations sharing a
long common border is a recipe
for tensions possibly war
and instability especially when the
border is undemarcated because China
insists on never demarcating the border
India Tibet border and
they are bolstering their western front
which is the India Tibet border that
area they are building more air bases
they are uh they have this cold start
strategy, cold start doctrine that they
are trying to adopt which means that the
moment an order is given to go to war
from Beijing within let's say 6 to 12
hours the war should start the troops
should not take a couple of days 48
hours 36 72 hours to mobilize
so the Chinese are getting better and
better at this and that is a matter of
great concern for India grave concern
for India and while China may no longer
be the master of Pakistan because now
the US is the master of Pakistan. Yet
China and Pakistan still see eye to eye
over India. Even the US and China see
eye to eye on India. They don't want
India to become too large for its own
boots.
The US only sees one value in India as a
counterbalance to China in some way. So
if there is instability, if there's a
border war, if there is whatever, it
benefits the US because it damages both
India and China. Now which if China
calculates that they can get away with
war with India without too much damage
to them they would like to go for it. I
would say that the Chinese are more
likely to start a war with India than
start a war start a war about Taiwan
because if they start if they try to
invade Taiwan they will have to fight
the United States. If they try to fight
India the US is not going to get
involved. Neither is Russia because
Russia can't afford to. So it makes more
sense for them for Xiinping to to go to
war with India over let's say Pradesh
because they claim it's their territory
right. So what should India do and if in
in case there's a war with China the
Pakistanis are guaranteed to try and
play some mischief.
So how should we tackle it? Well I can't
tell you how we should tackle it. What
we should do is we should be prepared
for a two and a half three front
scenario at all times. We need to have
adequate stockpiles of various kinds of
missiles.
Several thousand Brahos missiles, maybe
10,000 Brahmosh missiles. See a thousand
missiles. Look at the Ukraine war. How
many missiles are being used every day?
If you have 300 Brahmos missiles in your
stockpile, it's going to last you 3
hours potentially, you know, in the case
of a hot war. So, we need potentially
tens of thousands of missiles in our
stockpile. Various kinds of missiles.
Missiles get consumed very fast in a hot
war and you always want a backup. You
can't start issue give an order to start
production. Now that takes time to
produce all this stuff. So whether it is
the bramos missiles, whether it is
various kinds of ballistic missiles,
other kinds of cruise missiles, uh
whether it is the u whatever artillery,
ammunition, we need to have sufficient
stockpiles for at least a 3-month war in
which we can use as much ammunition and
missiles as required and all the all
three fronts. That's what we should be
prepared for. And we should be prepared
for you know going to war at at like a
two two hour notice.
The army should not be in a in a
situation where they will take two days
to mobilize properly. It should be quick
reaction. So that's how you prepare for
it. And I'm sure the the armed forces
are doing everything that is needed for
this to do to to happen in case such a
scenario eventuates.
Rit Pawar says how can one avoid
comparing oneself to others and remain
focused on personal goals despite
outside noise and others others
achievements.
How do you avoid comparing yourself with
others? I think you have to train
yourself to do that.
There's always the the temptation to
compare yourself with other people in
your domain, in your industry, in uh
whatever field you're working in.
There's always the temptation. Let me
see what that person is doing. Oh my
god, that person is doing great and I'm
not doing it. Boohoo. All that stuff.
So, what you have to do is you have to
set a goal for yourself and focus on the
goal.
And the goal should be something that
really motivates you. You should not
have to listen to motivational YouTube
videos to get motivation.
The goal should be deeply personal for
you. It should be difficult to achieve
but not impossible to achieve. And you
should break the goal down into multiple
pieces. Let's say 3 month, three month,
three month kind of you know quarterly
targets or whatever you want to have it
and a big at the end of the year target
that sort of thing and work towards
that. If you are fully immersed in that
struggle, that personal struggle of
yours, then you will not have the time
to look at other people. And uh you need
to have a very clear schedule, a very
clear uh daily schedule, daily routine,
whatever. You need to create systems for
yourself that help you achieve what
you're doing.
So it's a process. It's not going to
happen overnight that you suddenly
change.
You will not wake up tomorrow morning
decide. Let's say you make a decision
today. I'll stop comparing myself to
others and I'll focus on my goals. But
that doesn't happen overnight. You to
first take the time to define the goals
that matter to you.
Most people think they have goals but
they see what kind of goal should you
set for yourself. H let's say you are a
YouTuber. Let's say I'm in in the field
of YouTube right now, right? I could
have a goal that next year I want to
have 2 million subscribers by 31st
December. Okay? I could set a goal like
that potentially. I by the end by by
December 31st 2026 I want to have I
should have anyhow 2 million
subscribers. Okay, let's say I set a
goal like that. Now tell me does this
goal make sense.
Is it in my hand? Is it in my control
whether you subscribe or not? That is
your decision. And there are other
factors like the YouTube algorithm and
various wonderful people in YouTube who
who have who have give you know put a
limit of 950,000 on my channel right
now. So if I have that sort of goal it
is something that is not in my control.
So that's not the kind of goal you have
to set for yourself. You have to set
goals for yourself that are completely
in your control. So if you're a YouTuber
you can say next year I will publish x
number of videos
or if you are in some other industry
some other business whatever you have to
choose goals that you can achieve
on by yourself without external help
because external help is always
something that is not in your control
entirely. So only focus on what you
yourself can do and leave the rest to
the gods. [snorts]
So when you when you do that then it
becomes something you can entirely
control at least what you're doing like
Lord Krishna said to Arjun you do your
thing forget about everything else
you forget on you you you focus on your
karma on your actions and leave the fa
of the actions the fruit of the actions
to the gods leave it to them that is not
in your control you do what you have to
do and forget the rest so that's what
you have to do that's the That's the
philosophy you have to adopt.
And so set big goals, goals that you can
achieve on your own, what things you
will do.
And that is definitely achievable. So
once you once you realize that that you
know maybe in the past I was setting
goals that are not in my control and now
I'm setting goals that are 100% in my
control that will give you that extra
motivation and then you just focus on
that.
So, so that's kind of how you do things
and even that is difficult unless you
create systems, you know, systems that
take you towards that goal. That's a
whole different topic. So, that's what
you have to do and it's a process. You
learn over time. It's you're not going
to learn in by watching a YouTube video
how to do these things. You're not going
to learn by by reading an article how to
do these things. You're going to have to
start working on that.
Try things maybe fail here and there
maybe then m make improvements and maybe
in a few months you will have a system
that actually works and then you will be
on track towards your goals that's how
you do it so all the best Rik do well
achieve your goals minimalist vick says
Balojasthan and synind have 90% Islamic
population how to prevent Bangladesh 2.0
Bangladesh 2.0
I'm not able to understand how do you
prevent Bangladesh 2.0 and BJ and Synind
B see Bangladesh 2.0
Bangladesh
I I'm not really able to understand what
you're saying what you're asking
Bangladesh 1.0 Z was the
V section of Pakistan. We defeated
Pakistan in 1971 and broke Bangladesh
away from Pakistan. It it and and
converted East Pakistan into Bangladesh.
So you want to prevent that from
happening in Balucha 7. I'm not really
sure what you're asking. Maybe if you
can phrase your answer, phrase your
question properly then I'll be able to
understand what you're saying, sir.
Sorry. Basar bandit says no statements
or reaction from US on Vladimir
Vladimir's visit to BAT a potential
indication that Ukraine war will start
to ease now and focus of US to shift
more towards containing China and India.
Question mark
see I'm not surprised that the US has
not issued any statements about Vladimir
Vladimir's visit to Bharat. uh obviously
this is a bilateral matter and uh
this is something that's good for India
as well as for Russia and uh the US will
generally keep quiet about that
is this an indication that the Ukraine
war will start to ease now it's nothing
to do with that
Putin's visit to Bhat is independent of
the Ukraine war obviously the Ukraine
war will be discussed
and a lot of things will be discussed
would have been discussed but Because
Putin came to India and the US kept
quiet. Doesn't mean that the Ukraine war
is not going to ease up.
It will ease up depending on how the US
and the EU um
what actions they take going forward.
Right? See the US now now Trump wants to
end the war but the EU doesn't want to
end it. The EU is handin glove with Mr.
Zilinski
and that's a big in impediment in the
in the in the way of ending the Ukraine
war.
So will the do I see the Ukraine war
ending soon? I think it will end by the
end of 2026.
It will definitely
end it should definitely end by the end
of 2026. Hopefully it ends soon.
Hopefully next week or something. But
that hope is the probability of that
happening is very low because
of the attitude of the EU and and what's
his name? Zalinski. Zalinski. See if the
if the Ukraine war ends, it is very it's
going to be very difficult for Zilinski
well to stay relevant or maybe even to
survive. He'll have to go into exile.
He'll have to go to the west or
somewhere in Europe or wherever. He
won't be able to stay in Ukraine.
He will lose all the power that he has.
He will use he will lose whatever
sources of income he has. I'm sure he
has amassed tremendous amounts of money
and what not.
So the end of the Ukraine war is is
going to be something that will be very
dangerous personally for Mr. Zalinski.
Now the US doesn't care about Zilinski.
They have thrown so many dictators under
the bus in the past. They've personally
executed dictators like Saddam Hussein
and they've had people like Gaddafi
taken out and so much more. So the US
doesn't care about Zalinski. He's just a
disposable pawn for them. But for
Zalinski, he matters, right? And the EU,
all those little puppet minions who are
the leaders of the EU nations, they are
handin with Zalinsky. They want him to
remain relevant and in power and the US
will have to manage that.
And obviously the US doesn't want Russia
to become too powerful by gaining too
much territory etc. So that's the
situation. So I don't see the Ukraine
war ending very soon. I am hopeful it
will end by the end of 2026. It will be
great if it ends sooner because it will
be you know this it's been a
humanitarian disaster but I don't see it
ending very soon right now because of
all these reasons. uh once the Ukraine
war ends what does the US do towards
about India and China the US is already
implementing its strategy or policy of
containing India that's what it is doing
with China they have a different set of
strategy they use nice words and you
know all that they had a meeting
recently etc but the US sees China as
their primary adversary now and that is
not going to change so they may say nice
temporarily but uh
now they are using Japan as as as a pike
to prod China with right
so that's going to continue okay
critical thinker says I am 26 male I
want to continue my career in research
you have a master's degree in the Indian
Institute of Science IISC Bangalore
aerospace is it worth it outside India
is out of my budget. My only option
option is loan.
Look, how do you determine if something
is worth it? Let's say you have
three courses of action. Plan A, plan B,
plan C. Okay? And you have to make one
choice. You have to pick one of the
three things. Then if you pick one of
the three things maybe plan if you say
let's say you you pick plan A then maybe
plan B plan C after 6 months after 1
year will not be available to you. So
you have to make a careful decision what
to do in life. I'm 26. I'm no longer 18
and I have a master's degree in the from
in aerospace from the IC which is good
which is a great asset to have and I
want to continue my career in research.
Aerospace research I assume and going
out of India is beyond your budget
unless you take a loan a loan which is
obviously a gamble potentially a gamble.
What should you do?
So how do you determine which is the
best option?
The best option is going to be something
that's going to be valuable for you for
a long time.
You have to start with the most
practical questions.
Whatever option you take, is it going to
give you sufficient money
to live a respectable etc good lifestyle
or will you
will you have cash constraints or
whatever. Let's say you want to continue
a career in research within India.
So if that is the choice you want to
make, will that give you a stable career
with good with a with a good income with
a good salary?
That's the question. Then how do you
answer the question? You ask yourself
how many aerospace startups and
companies and institutions do we have in
India? We have DRDO, we have H. These
are governmentrun companies um
institutions and to get into that you
have to go through god knows what way.
um then you you could perhaps
go into some university in case there is
some research being done in India
somewhere but in Indian universities re
research is trash mostly in 98% of
India's universities research is is
there's no research happening it's only
namesake research then what about
startups how many startups do we have in
India that are doing high quality
research in the in the aerospace domain
I am not sure so I have not looked into
these things so I can't give you
specific speific answers but this is how
you have to look into it and let's say
you have x number of good highquality
aerospace startups or companies in India
where high quality research is happening
then the question is will you be able to
get into that based on the
qualifications that you have clearly a
master's degree in from the ISC is a
very good qualification maybe you'll be
able to get into that sure will you then
have long-term job stability or will you
have to do job hopping from one place to
another every one year two years is that
going to be a you know potential
situation and will they will the salary
be good enough. These are the questions
you to ask yourself. So I don't have the
answers because I've not done any
research in this in this field. So I
can't say but this is how you approach
it. Now let's say you take a loan and go
abroad.
So then the question is which country do
you go to? I mean obviously the best
country to go to is the US because
there's tremendous amount of aerospace
research etc happening there. But the US
doesn't like immigrants anymore. So what
about some other country? What other
countries are there? And if you go and
get a job there based on your
qualifications,
then how long will you be able to hold
on to the job? So does it does this make
does it does it make taking a loan and
going abroad too risky? So these are the
things the factors you to consider. I
can't give you an answer. I don't know
your specific circumstances. I am not
very familiar with the aerospace sector
in India. I have not done any research
in that what the what are the job
prospects, career prospects like so I
can't tell you but that's how you have
to do your research and uh yeah do that
and I wish you the best. I wish you
great success in your career sir.
Okay, critical thinker says does a super
massive black hole consume dark matter?
How do they grow big? What kind of
research do we do at space stations? We
do we need space stations or space
telescopes? Okay, how many questions do
we have in one? Do super massive black
holes consume dark matter? They consume
everything.
Whether it's a super massive black hole
or a stellar mass black hole,
intermediate mass black hole or even a
primordial microscopic black hole. Black
holes are black holes. They have the
same properties. They the properties of
a black hole from the outside are given
by only three quantities.
Mass, charge, angular momentum. That's
it. And they all behave the same way. So
whatever comes their way, if it is if it
crosses the event horizon, they're going
to swallow it. Gobble gobble. So whether
it is
gas, whether it is dust, whether it is
planets, whether it's stars, whether
it's dark matter, they will eat
everything. Okay, that's how it happens.
How do super massive black holes grow
big? Well, it is believed, the best
theory is that super massive black holes
start
as from primordial black hole seeds.
What are primordial black holes? tiny
microscopic black holes that are
believed to have been produced in
tremendous numbers in the very early
universe in the first few seconds of the
existence of the universe. So those
primordial black holes
they they most likely did
get produced they would have been
produced because of quantum fluctuations
in the very early universe. We still
have quantum fluctuations vacuum today
and those primordial black holes
eventually would have formed the seeds
of what are now super massive black
holes which seem to be at the heart of
most
most galaxies today. So that's uh about
super massive black holes. What kind of
research do we do at space stations? Uh
microgravity research, research on human
aging, research on how bacteria and
microorganisms behave in microgravity.
Uh how do plants grow in microgravity?
how do various other materials um what
kind of stresses and strains do they
experience in microgravity
um and things like that that's that's
the kind of research you do at space
stations you also study the the space
climate you study the kind of radiation
that you experience near the van allen
belts there are two van alen belts that
we have around the earth because of
earth's magnetic field we study cosmic
rays if you are let's say
depending on the height you
above above the earth's surface. You do
different kinds of experiments and
different kind of studies and so on. So
so that's that's what you do. Uh do we
need space station or space telescopes?
Depending on what you want to achieve,
right? You can just put a space
telescope up there out there and it will
look out into the cosmos and depending
on its capabilities, it will, you know,
give you various kinds of data. So we
have the Hubble Space Telescope that's
it's been around since the late 1980s or
something and it still does great work
you know and you have the James Web
Space Telescope that is behind that's in
the Earth's shadow behind behind the
Earth you know and it's a very very
high-tech telescope the latest that we
have and it's already revolutionized our
understanding of the cosmos. So that's
space telescopes. Do we need in space
stations? Space telescopes depending on
what you want to do. If you need human
involvement for a long time in space,
you will need space stations. Space
stations are they have a geopolitical
purpose more than a scientific purpose.
And space stations are mostly scientific
instruments. Anik says
first part watch Durand. I know you
don't watch Indian films, but this is a
banger. Raw, real yet entertaining.
Exposes Pakistani and 0.5 front mindset.
Okay. Thank you very much for this
recommendation.
>> Maybe I'll watch it. Okay.
And part two, Sikit, I remember one time
you stated the real reason of
demonetization, fake currency from
Pakistan. They also added this in the
film. Well, very interesting. Looks like
I'll have to check this movie out. I've
heard a lot of good things about this
movie on social media. Everyone's
praising it. So maybe I'll make an
exception to my rule of not watching
Indian movies and maybe I'll go and
watch it. So thank you Anik for the
recommendations. really appreciate that.
Minimalist Maverick says, "What's your
height? How does it matter? I'm 6'1."
Uh, what and how is your fitness
routine? You said you having one meal a
day and five rest of the day. Um, these
days my fitness routine is not that
routine. Yeah, I need to I need to get
back on track and be a little more
disciplined. Typically, my fitness
routine is that I lift like five times,
six times a week. when I used to be very
disciplined. That's what I was doing.
When was the last time I was properly
properly disciplined about this? I think
2019. It's been like five years since
I've been reasonably undisiplined about
this. After the pandemic happened and
this gyms shut down for like 2 three
years. Yeah. That that totally disrupted
my fitness routine. Until 2019, I was
super jacked. I was uh today not so
much. Yeah. And yeah, it's not always
one meal a day day for me these days. I
need to get back on track on those
things, you know. Uh yeah, so typically
I would eat one meal a day. I would make
sure I get 150 plus grams of protein,
maybe almost 200 grams of protein. Uh I
don't have fiber the rest of the day.
No, I don't. If I ate one meal a day,
it's one meal a day. I eat whatever I
eat within a 1 hour window and that's
it. Done. Done. And don't think about
food after that. And I would lift five
or six days a week different routines
you know I I have my own I understand
how how my body works and I have my own
six day five day or six day split
routine various body parts various kinds
of exercises I uh prefer barbells over
dumbbells just a personal preference
that sort of thing
and you are 5' 11 19 male jacked
outstanding I really appreciate being
jacked
uh yeah you should be see about being
jacked you don't have to ripped. You
don't need to have like 5% body fat or
10% body fat. It's okay to have 15 or
even 20% body fat, but you need to be
physically strong. You don't have to be
able to show all the striations in your
pecs and and traps and all that. You
don't need to do that. Your abs don't
necessarily need to be clearly visible,
but you need to be strong.
So, there's two terms. One is jacked,
one is yolked. You should be yolked. You
should be able to lift heavy weights.
You should when you have the capacity to
lift really heavy weights, not I'm not
saying 500 kilos and thing, but like
unreasonably heavy weights like 150
kilos or whatever deadlift that sort of
thing. Then that gives you a totally
different kind of confidence. So that's
what you need. The the point is it's not
why do you lift? Why do you get strong?
It's not to beat somebody up. It's not
to have a certain appearance. It's just
to feel great about yourself. It's just
to know that if needed, I can do things.
That's another thing. So that's the
whole point of uh of getting strong. The
objective should not be to show an eight
pack or to have clearly visible
striations in your various muscles etc.
The objective is to get strong like
really strong. That's the objective.
That's how I see it. Anyway, it's up to
you. Uh, if you want to have an eight
pack and whatnot, all for it. It's
entirely up to you. But my philosophy is
get strong, like really strong. You
don't have to be ripped down to the bone
marrow.
Tesh Pande says, "Big fan as we know our
history." Thank you. Uh, I want to ask
about Pawan.
Um yeah, in my opinion the greatest
battle ever with 270 Maratas versus
15,000 Adil Shahis. I assume non Maratis
do not know about this. No offense, I
have not studied Marata history in
detail.
So yeah, I don't know anything
significant about Pawan Kind. It's it's
one aspect of Indian history that I am
yet to study in any kind of detail. I
have the books. I have acquired the
books
and the books that I see
uh there is this uh
there's a writer
Italian writer
Ombberto
he had this concept called the anti
library.
So he owned I don't know tens of
thousands of books and many of the books
that he had in his bookshelves he had
not read them yet. So the point the
question is why would you buy books that
you
why would you keep buying books when you
have so many books you've not read and
the point is that it it kind of tempers
your your ego
that there's so much that you don't know
about and it also motivates you you know
get the work done find the time to read
this book that book I've been waiting to
read that so I also have that sort of
concept if you look at the books here
all the physics books I've chewed
through them multiple times But there
are other books that I have in other
parts of my library and other library in
other rooms that I haven't read yet and
I still keep ordering books from time to
time. So I
yeah so I have read more books than I
own and I own more books than and I buy
more books than I can read essentially.
But yeah so I have books about Marata
history but I haven't got around to
reading them yet. So that's why I won't
be able to answer this question but uh
sounds really interesting and hopefully
I can soon find the time to read about
this.
Bijua says will AI ever become conscious
like humans?
I'm not sure if AI will be conscious
like humans. It's possible that AI could
become self-aware. Maybe it is
self-aware and we are not aware of it.
See there's something called the Turing
test.
Um the great
English
computer scientist Alan Turing came up
with this concept. So the touring test
is that let's say you have a curtain,
okay? And you don't know what's the
other side of the curtain. You only have
a screen on your side and a keyboard and
you can input you can type stuff into
the into the keyboard and see it
displayed on the screen and you press
enter and you asking a question to
whoever is on the other side and then
the then whoever is on the other side
will respond to you and based on the
interaction that you're having with
whatever is on the other side. If you
can't tell whether the entity on the
other side is human or not,
then whatever is on the other side has
passed the during test. If it's a
computer, it's passed the Turing test.
So today, we have a situation where AI
has passed the Turing test. Most people
who are not aware of how AI talks and
communicates won't want to know whether
it's a person or not. AI can be really
profound these days in its uh
communication with humans. So AI, I
would say, has already passed the
touring test unless you keep on
redefining the touring test every 6
months, which is nonsense. AI has passed
the Turing test but is AI conscious and
that that's a question we don't quite
know. We don't quite have the answer to.
I would imagine that the computer
scientists working with the v various AI
companies would have a better
understanding of whether AI is conscious
or not. They some companies have
something called AI wellness. They don't
want to expose AI to too much abuse or
whatever. Some users apparently use
harsh language with AIS and maybe it's
it's harmful to the AI which would
indicate that AI has feelings which
would indicate that it's kind of
conscious like humans I don't know
but even if AI does become self-aware
and conscious will it be conscious the
way we are conscious
what are the components or elements of
our consciousness
our senses are an integral part of our
consciousness
right how do we sense the
We sense the external world through
vision, through sight, through sound,
through touch,
through smell, through taste. Five sense
organs, right? AI can't sense the world
that way. So even if it's conscious,
it's going to be conscious in a very
different, very alien way from the way
we are conscious.
Biju says, "What's your favorite
football club?" I don't really have a
favorite football club right now. I
haven't watched football in any
seriousness for like almost a couple of
decades.
Yeah. I mean at different points in time
when I was in college, university etc. I
had different I used to perhaps at a
time
see mainly in India it's the EPL that
you see right the English Premier
League. So there was a time when I used
to kind of be little bit partial towards
Liverpool when Michael Owen used to
play. He's now an he's now a pandit
commentator
and I liked Arsenal when Arsenal when a
winger was the boss the gaffer and uh
was their main guy was fun to watch him.
I
kind of was fond of the way Manchester
United played when Eric Ktona was the
main guy. Yes. also when uh vantoy
was one of their main players and so on.
So I've had I've watched various
football clubs. I I just like good good
sport, artistry,
killer instinct, all of that. And
whoever does that, I like that. I don't
have one favorite football club right
now. I don't watch any football anymore.
I don't watch any of that these days.
The most I would do is once in a while
watch a little bit of sports somewhere.
Maybe I watched the last 20 minutes of
the Ashes test match. That was fun. H
the the palms terrible, terrible. And
let's not talk about the Indian cricket
team right now. What are they doing in
the test match arena? Especially at home
especially. Anyway, King Ritik says,
"Suggest best peaceful beach." Beach to
visit. What beach? Peaceful. [laughter]
Okay. S
Uh is it Gokarna, Karnataka or Varcala,
Kerala, Puri, Odisha or any other place?
Can't afford expensive Andaman?
I don't know.
I I
don't know. I'm told Goa has great
beaches,
but I'm sure there are lots of other
places in India that have great beaches,
too. But I personally haven't spent time
on beaches. I would love to. The last
time I was at a beach was when probably
at Prabhaspatan Sumnath
and I spent about half an hour on the
beach with the water up to my up to my
knees only and I got sunburnt like my
arms one of my arms got like scarlet red
from a sunburn
and yeah I had a lot of my leg pulled
because I'm I'm supposed to be Indian.
I'm not supposed to get sunburnt. That's
supposed to happen to white people or
whatever. Anyhow, so uh I don't know. I
don't have so much experience with
Indian beaches. So I can't say but if
you like mountains, I will definitely
recommend Ladak.
Amir Mishra says, "Government instead of
being aggressive showed a very
reactionary, non-escalatory stance in
operation Hindu. Does it lack the will
to move beyond occasional retaliation
and pursue a firm long-term decisive
action against Pakistan?"
See, we have to remember that we have
allowed this godamned temporary
artificial nation to acquire nuclear
weapons. Whichever way they acquired it,
we could have ended that nuclear
dream of theirs in the 1980s.
We should have done that. How can you
allow a terrorist nation to acquire
nuclear weapons?
So, we missed the bus.
Today, it is a nuclear weapon state.
Whether they acquired the nuclear
weapons from China or North Korea or
most likely from the United States
today, it doesn't matter. It's a nuclear
weapon state
and that's why we have to be careful.
That's the first thing I can tell you
that we have to take this matter
seriously that they have nuclear
weapons. You just start bombarding
everything maybe they will be tempted to
launch a nuclear weapon at you. Now the
question is do we look Pakistan
launching nuclear strikes on India will
maybe uh cause significant damage to a
few Indian cities. They will want to
strike at the major Indian cities. Sure,
of course, India can take the damage.
It will be horrific damage.
But that will be the end of Pakistan
because we will wipe them out. But the
question is, will it not set us back
like a decade or two economically,
right? I'm sure we may even be able to
intercept most of their nuclear missiles
or whatever. But even then, do we want
to take that risk?
Even if we flatten Pakistan but we have
lost a few cities, it will not feel like
a victory for us. Right? So the point is
how do we deal with this nation?
That's the question.
You can be all aggressive and you know
you know see the problem with these
Indian analysts is that they they think
that war is harsh words and robust
language all that [snorts]
blah blah blah etc. That's not war. That
is just you hankering after views on
YouTube. That's all. I mean they turn
everything into entertainment.
Everything has to be entertaining for
the viewer.
But that's not the reality of the world.
The reality is that we have to manage
the risks and we have allowed the
Pakistanis to have nuclear weapons. So
now what do we do about this? The best
thing is to have Pakistan break up from
within without us going to war with
them. And if we do fight a war, it has
to be a very rapid blitzkrieg kind of
war which ends in maximum 48 hours. So I
think in operation zindur the objective
was to give a bloody nose to Pakistan by
destroying a bunch of terrorist camps
and killing a few hundred terrorists and
maybe doing a little more damage. Beyond
that it wasn't I was hopeful that we'll
take some portion of P or something but
clearly that was not the military
objective.
So it's not like India lacks the will to
move beyond occasional retaliation etc.
It's like
most likely operation sindur had limited
objectives just to give Pakistan a
bloody nose. There was no objective of
taking territory back from Pakistan and
there was no objective to end in a
regime change in Pakistan.
So it was a limited operation
right
but the next time some terri some
territory should change hands you can't
have a score line in a in a India
Pakistan war 70 or 32 or whatever you
shot down these many planes we shot down
this that's not how a war works
so hopefully next time there'll be a
different kind of outcome
says what are the top three biggest
blunders India did in the last 75 years
number one okay in no particular order
we allowed Pakistan to acquire nuclear
weapons. I mean what the hell was that?
Yeah. Secondly, we did not
weaponize our nuclear capabilities in
1974. Why? We tested a nuclear weapon in
1974. Then we went to sleep until 1998.
If we had tested nuclear weapons 30 40
times by 1998
then we would have been regarded very
differently today.
Right? Uh it would have made India way
more powerful nation a long time ago.
There is that
what other blunders allowing a 100
million Bangladeshies to enter India and
settle down in various parts of India.
What the hell is that?
Right. And lastly, we did not decolonize
at all. We are more colonized today than
we were in 1947. They have imposed the
English language all across India. You
can't get a good job unless you speak
English. Well,
the education system is further
colonizing us. The entire bureaucracy,
the entire Indian state apparatus is
fully colonial in nature. All the
institutions were created by the
British. We have never decolonized
because of that. Indian citizens have
this massive inferiority complex and
then we have I can go on forever. It
will be more than three blenders but you
ask for three I'll give it I'll give you
[laughter] three.
Okay. Al Janib says if karma is
quantifiable in the reality as we know
will Pakistan ever cease to exist with
the scale of the misdeeds its misdeeds
towards India so far regardless of
whatever reasons it gets to live another
day. Look I don't know about karma.
Is karma quantifiable? Look, if karma is
a is a real thing.
Hopefully it is. Yeah,
that's all what our ancestors taught us.
It's part of our civilizational
heritage, cultural heritage. Karma karma
is a conservation law.
the it's a conservation laws that says
that the merits and demerits of your
actions in the world
stay with you
across multiple lifetimes.
That's the law of karma.
And that explains actually kind of a lot
of things. But
it's it's philosophy, it's spirituality,
it's religion. It's not science. But it
is a conservation law unlike any other
religion. No other religion will give
you a conservation law. It's a
conservation law. Um but the thing is
you can get away with a lot of things
even if you're evil in your current
life.
You may have to pay the price in future
lifetimes.
That's the law of karma. That that's
sometimes how it works, right? So there
are plenty of nasty people who are so
successful and they never pay a price
for anything. But maybe they do in in in
future lifetimes, subsequent lifetimes.
So and and remember which yoga we are
living in. This is Kali Yuga which means
that he will succeed during this yoga.
It looks like.
So my point is let's not put our faith
in the law of karma. Let us ourselves be
the bearer of karma.
If you want justice in the world,
don't pray to the gods to give you
justice while you while you are passive.
be active. Don't be passive. You be the
justice the gods visit on the earth.
So I am not this big big fan of you know
let karma do its thing and Pakistan will
pay someday. No, we make it pay.
Let us be the shadow of the gods on the
planet and let us make things happen in
the name of the gods.
Okay. Uh, Moran
Moran
Moran says E4 or D4.
You're talking about chess. What are you
talking about?
Not sure what the question is. Is this a
chess move?
Is it something else? I'm I'm not really
sure. Sorry.
Gapati says, "Who is Emperor Barat? Why
is India named after him?" Emperor
Barat. who is well he isn't anymore he
was Emperor Barat right
um
one of our great kings
what was his story
Emperor Barat
I'm a little hazy on that right now
[laughter]
[clears throat] yeah maybe another time
vidar says IMF has put Russia down to
slow down foreign foreign investment.
IMF has put Russia down
to slow down foreign investment.
How have they put Russia down
to slow down foreign investment in
Russia?
Russia wasn't anyway encouraging a lot
of foreign investment. Right.
Um once again I'm not really sure what
you are saying or asking Vidi G. IMF,
how have they put Russia down? What is
the meaning of putting someone down?
When it comes to animals, it has a
pretty nasty meaning actually to put an
animal down.
Um, not very clear about what you're
saying. Sorry. Biju says, "Usually oil
rich countries are dictatorships. Why is
Norway not under a dictatorship even
though it's oil rich?"
Let's talk about oil rich countries.
Saudi Arabia it's a monarchy sure
dictatorship of various Gulf nations all
monarchies or dictatorships sure
Nigeria is oil rich where is
dictatorship they have what seems to be
some form of democracy there
Venezuela
is Maduru a dictator well the US will
say he's a dictator but he was elected
right wasn't he so look if the west
calls somebody a dictator does it mean
that they are really dictator they call
a dictator Putin was elected.
I mean, Joe Biden, Donald Trump, Donald
Trump claims
he stole the election. So that's
dictatorship, isn't it?
So
what about Norway? Norway is a
socialistic kind of nation. So my point
is there is no such hard and fast rule
that oil rich nations have to be
dictatorships.
I don't agree with that.
So therefore the question is moot.
Norway is a is a socialistleaning
uh democracy.
Of course it's part of the EU which
means it's not really a sovereign
nation. They are under a dictatorship.
Norway is under the Brussels
dictatorship. By the way Brussels is a
dictatorship. It's not a democracy.
Madame
she keeps on saying dictatorship.
democracy is there's a democracy and we
must have democracy in the world but she
is a dictator who is imposing her agenda
on the happless people of the EU
including the people of Norway
so Norway is actually under a
dictatorship it's under the EU
dictatorship
Rahul AK says what was the entropy of
the universe just after its formation
before the formation of fundamental
particles did the formation of
fundamental particles increase the
entropy or decrease it. Okay,
interesting question. What was the
entropy? We don't know what the entropy
was, but did the entropy increase? Of
course, it increased.
Once again, let me explain what entropy
is. I will try not to bring the
rhinosaurus down this time. What is
entropy? Even those of you who have no
interest in physics, I hope that I'll
make this understandable to you. There
is a concept called entropy in physics,
in thermodynamics. Okay. What does
entropy mean? If you open a physics
textbook at whatever level, maybe sixth
standard, 8th standard, college,
whatever, they will say it will say
entropy is a measure of disorder.
What does that mean? You may understand
what it means if you have a background
in physics. If you are reading for the
first time, you will have you'll be able
to make no sense of it. So, let me
explain in a different way. Look at this
room behind me. Very orderly room,
right? I've got these books here. I've
got this little rhinosaurus here. I've
got a couple of dinosaurs there.
Everything is nicely orderly in kept in
a nice orderly way. Now if I were to
bring some books down, boom. If I were
to throw some clothes up here, you will
immediately notice the small changes,
right? If my if my
friend the rhinosaurus falls down, you
will notice it. If the dinosaur comes
down from here to there, you will notice
it. So in a very orderly room, even
small changes will be noticeable
immediately by you. But let's say we are
in a different room. Completely messy
room. Okay. The books are strewn across
the floor. The books are on the bed. The
clothes are on the floor. The clothes
are on the bookshelves. Cables hanging
everywhere. Dust everywhere.
Stationary pens thrown everywhere.
Absolute godamned mess.
Okay. Now, if I rearrange the room in a
different kind of mess, will you notice?
You will most likely not notice. Right?
So if you have a system where even small
changes become are easily noticeable
that is that that system is has low
entropy where even small changes become
easily noticeable. But if you have a
system where you have a if you make
major changes but you can't notice
anything
then that system has high entropy more
disorder. This is an orderly room that
is a messy room disorderly room. So when
we talk about systems, we're talking
about systems like a box of gas or a
glass of water. A glass of water has
billions of molecules. A box, a room
containing gas, like the atmospheric gas
that they breathe, it has trillions of
molecules.
So if I make some kind of major
microscopic level change in the room,
let's say I have a box containing gas
and I shake it around, it will
completely reconfigure the microscopic
configurations of the gas, right? Of the
gas molecules. But you will notice not a
thing. It means it has high entropy. And
if I take a frozen piece of let's say an
ice cube
which has low entropy because it's all
crystalline and I put it in a glass of
water you will immediately see the
change it will start melting. So that
has so the entropy is going from low to
high. So that is entropy. Now hopefully
you understand what is entropy and how
it is a measure of disorder. So a system
where you can make lots of changes, lots
of reconfiguration of the micro
microscopic level without you noticing
anything, it's a system with high
entropy. Now entropy always goes from
low to high. The second law of
thermodynamics says that any in any
system entropy either stays the same or
increases. It can never decrease.
So one such system is the universe.
It's the biggest system that we have out
there. So we don't know what the
specific entropy what the specific
measure of entropy was at a certain
point in time of the universe.
But if it is just after its formation
and before the formation of fundamental
particles
so the entropy of the universe before
something is always going to be less
than after something.
Okay. So the formation of fundamental
particles etc increase the entropy. It
was not the specifically the formation
of fundamental particles. It was the
expansion of the universe.
Why did fundamental particles form?
Because the universe was expanding and
cooling which caused more entropy. So
overall the entropy increased increased
and one of the consequences of that was
the formation of fundamental particles.
It's the other way around.
Okay.
Anime says mixed news about six Rafal
getting shot. What are my views? I don't
have any views on this. In any war
you're going to lose some assets. So
what's the big godamn deal
in the 1971 war? How many air air assets
did we lose? More than 60 70, right? Who
won the war? We won the war. If we are
going to be so risk others that we can't
take a few something or the other
getting shot
then we will not achieve anything in the
in the world.
So I don't care if X number or Y number
or Z number of Rafals were lost or not
lost. It doesn't matter. Overall, we won
the three-day war, operation sindur. We
did way more damage to Pakistan. And
where is the evidence of these destroyed
Rafals? First of all, we have very
clear-cut evidence of all the missile
strikes all across Pakistan on the
Pakistani military assets. Show me one
evidence of the of Rafal getting shot.
So, first of all, there is lack of
evidence. And secondly, even if
something like this happened, I don't
care. We came out on top. We can buy 100
more Rafals, thousand more Rafals if you
want to. If the government has the
willingness to do it, we have the money
that's what we should be doing. Okay. Uh
UMX Gluha says Russia co-developed the
Brahos missile but themselves don't use
it. Why? They use the PAT Onyx which is
the father of the Brahos.
Have you heard of the PAT Onyx?
So we use the more advanced one. They
use an older one. They also use the the
Siron missile which is a more advanced
version. Okay. P80
Onyx.
Okay. It's 800 P800 onx uh Yakant. Yeah,
they still use it if I am not mistaken.
It is a replacement for the Moskita and
it is the
it's the as you can see it looks very
much like the bramos right. So the
bramos is an advanced version of this
more
of this older uh missile. Does it say
something? Yeah, it says about bramos.
And then they have the caliber missile.
So the Russians use the onyx or the
yakont which is the ancestor of the
bramos. And then they have developed
other missiles also like the tiron
missile which is a frightening missile.
I'm not sure that siron is is it cruise
missile? I think it's a cruise missile.
Right. Zircon missile.
It's a hypersonic cruise missile. Yeah.
Um the Russians use that. So the
Russians have been developing various
kinds of missiles and they use the ONIX
or the Yakont. They use the Turkon and
we are co-developing a different version
of the Brahmos with them. You know next
generation Brahmos. So that's how it is.
Gapati says India today female
journalists asked questions to
Putin that made him snap. I did not
watch the interview thankfully.
Men do diplomacy but women get to take
interviews. Men fight wars but women get
to do press interviews. State sponsored
emasculation won't end well. See I will
not want to look at this from the prism
or the lens of gender.
I would what I would say is send your
best journalists.
Stop talking about this gender's power
or that gender's power. Give everybody
the same treatment and whoever performs
best, send them to do the interview. In
India, we have this thing these days of
of putting women forward and everything.
I am not against women's empowerment
whatever. give everybody the same right
but don't give any gender preferential
treatment.
That's my point. That is wrong. Then you
are no longer giving everybody the same
starting point in that sort of thing.
There's no equality. Then
see this modern feminism 21st century
feminism is not about women's equality.
It's about putting women giving women
first preference and everything which is
wrong.
A society has to be merit-based
irrespective of your gender. If you are
good, you should get the reward for it.
That's all. So I I have I I consciously
decided not to watch this interview with
President Putin because I kind of knew
how it is going to go and that's why I
al I've also not not watched that
interview with uh Elon Musk
even though it's a male person who did
that but I kind of know how that will go
also. So um when you start giving
preferential treatment to Xgender or Y
gender it's going to cause problems in
society. give everybody the same
treatment. If a lady is better than 99
other male journalists, then let her go
and do the interview. But if a a male
person, a male, a man is better than
than that lady, then let him go. Don't
give people preferential treatment based
on their gender. I just don't get it. I
don't agree with that.
Right. So I I don't know. Did did these
questions make Putin snap? I would not
be surprised if that was the case.
See, another problem in India is that
overall this the the quality of India's
journalists is terrible.
It's terrible. They just if you go and
interview the president of Russia, you
need to have some basic understanding of
geopolitics beyond slogans
you know to actually understand what
Putin's interests are, what Russia's
interests are, where are the convergence
convergence between India and Russia,
you have to understand things in detail.
Only then can you have a proper
conversation with Vladimir Putin.
But Indian journalists are just shallow.
Shallow. [snorts] Absolutely shallow.
What can I say?
UMX Gloha says, "Is the Voyic manuscript
real or not?" It seems to be real, but I
don't know much about it. It's this
obscure strange manuscript that's
written in a weird script that nobody is
able to decipher. It is It has this
weird strange
fantastical paintings or or drawings on
it. Seems to be
something that that was created a few
centuries ago.
And is it real or not? Uh, look, I'm not
the right person to ask this. I haven't
really studied this manuscript in any
detail. Looks like
looks like it was created a few
centuries ago. But is it real? Is it is
it a hoax? Is it a joke? I
vss says what's your opinion on INR
depreciation as our re say? Please
Google. Okay. Is 95 to 105 and good for
exports? Waiting for understanding
America. Okay. What's R E R?
R E R What's R E R? Real effective
exchange rate an economic measures
showing a currency's value adjusted for
inflation against a basket of trading
partners currencies indicating trade
competitiveness but it can also be the
brand name for okay
okay weighted average of a currency's
exchange rate against other currencies
adjusted for inflation purpose measures
a country's international
competitiveness
a rising re suggests a strong currency
making exports pricier okay so let's say
we have in depreciation
our I E okay let's see what is our reer
of INR
okay what is what is CIC data let's take
a look quickly if it will ever open
okay it's 107.1 in October 2025
compared to the same number in the
previous month okay stop that
okay so the reer
is 107. It was 107 in October.
So the Indian rupee is depreciating
which is not bad if you are an exporter
export oriented country right
uh that way you get more money in terms
of Indian rupees. What's my opinion? I'm
not really sure about this. I'm I have
not studied the re e concept and I
anyway I'm not someone who
um has a background in economics. I I
won't be able to say
what is the exact uh
situation and what does it mean
economically. I would have to do some
research before I would be able to
answer you about this matter.
What's going on in Sindra Sudan? Is the
UAE really involved? So a couple of
weeks ago, maybe two, three episodes
ago, maybe four episodes ago, I answered
this in great detail.
What's going on in Sudan? If you want to
know which episode it is, I can kind of
tell you. Let me uh
let me open up
my channel
and I'll tell you which episode it is
in. And the timestamps are there so
you'll be able to go right over to the
matter instead of me answering the whole
entire question all over again.
I think it was was it this?
Which question? Which episode was it?
It was one of these uh Sudan Sudan.
Sudan dam.
So it was definitely not 308.
Was it 307
306? It is one of these episodes in
which I have answered this question in
great detail. Is is the UAE involved?
Who is involved? etc. I have answered
that. Um see I don't know if the UAE is
involved. If you want me to answer this
question, it'll take at least 10 15
minutes. So I took the time to answer
that. So please check out one of those
episodes and check out the timestamps.
You will find the answer.
Okay. Anonymous scientist says,
"Bonjour, hope you're doing great. I'm
doing great. Was occupied in work and
got flu. Will watch missed episodes."
All right. I hope you're getting better.
Even I got the flu last week. Uh one of
the last one of the live streams during
the last week.
I was not in very good shape. I was
sneezing and coughing etc. But
[laughter] you know what? Flu is a flu.
It goes away. So I hope you get well
soon sir and do watch the missed
episodes. Thank you anyway all as always
for your viewership. I really appreciate
that. Thank you sir.
Um, Saswat Alims says, "Trump Saswat
Ames says Trump self-awwarded himself
the FIFA Peace Prize." Really? What is
this now? Uh, although I would not be
surprised. Let's see. Trump, what did he
do?
Trump
FIFA Peace Prize. FIFA has a peace
prize. I was not aware of this. FIFA's
first peace prize goes to Donald Trump
in departure from its traditional focus
on sport. Oh, really? I mean why does
FIFA have to issue peace prizes? FIFA is
the international the football athletic
or something right?
Next year he wins the Lego peace prize.
He wins the Lego Lego peace prize.
What is the FIFA peace prize?
Why does FIF Why is FIFA in the business
of giving peace prizes? FIFA should be
giving football prizes. I don't know
man. So looks like they are
you know trying to keep Mr. Trump happy.
Rahul Kumar says should India resume
nuclear tests at least two off. Look if
other nations start it we should also
start. We should also resume. If we
start off on our own we will be hit by
sanctions with hit with sanctions from
the US. But if the US goes ahead then
the Russians go ahead then we should
also go ahead. So we will not be able to
initiate this. But if others start the
process of nuclear testing, if others
resume nuclear tests, then we should
immediately go ahead and do some tests
of our own.
James says, uh, the benefit of the
English English language in the modern
world is impeccable. It is so beneficial
that you can't even comprehend its
benefits. It's a blessing in disguise.
If you agree or not, it doesn't matter.
uh the benefit of the English language.
You see, let me show you something. Let
me tell you something peculiar about the
English language.
The English language is a language that
doesn't have a script of its own.
Now, you may disagree with me, but we
use the script. Look at this. A B C D H
E B E N E F. It's we have our own
script. Do you know what the script is
called?
This is the Latin script. It is a script
that originated in what is now Italy
and it was the script used by the Romans
for writing Latin. At that time there
was no England. You had the Celtic
peoples who lived in what is today
England in Western Europe and they did
not have a script of their own. They
were unwashed savages or maybe not.
Maybe they were more civilized than
maybe actually they were pretty
civilized. They had druids. They had
women had more rights for the among the
Celtic people in Celtic society compared
to post-Christian society in Europe.
Yeah. And so on. So the Kelts did not
have a script of their own and they
spoke various Celtic languages.
Uh some of the Celtic languages that do
survive are Irish, GI, Scots, the
Scottish language, etc. GIC
And you have the the Breton language in
France um and so on. And then you have
the Nordic people
who had their own script which is called
the runic script, the runic alphabet.
Now the Romans took over the world and
they imposed their foreign Latin script
on everybody else and you English
you use that for your language,
right? And the fact is that the Latin
script is not suitable for the English
language. I mean look at the absurdity
of the spellings in the English
language.
Terrible.
So the English language is so primitive.
It doesn't even have a script of its
own. It uses a borrowed script, a script
that came out of an italic language.
Whereas your language is a Germanic
language,
a rather inferior language. It's just
that you, a nation of shopkeepers, uh,
acquired armies and you were better for
some time in the systematic application
of violence, which is how you conquered
the world. And that's why for some time,
for a while, we're going to be using
your language, but eventually we will
revert to a more civilized language like
it used to be.
Anyway, James, I really do appreciate
you very much. Thank you.
Godliness says, "Gross in incompetence
and in discipline of the DGCA in regards
to the Indigo situation is shameful.
They lack any accountability. Clearly,
they're not competent to investigate the
AI the Air India Ahmedabad crash. The
AirIndia Ahmedabad crash. A report was
published and it was leaked to the
American media before
before it was even published in India,
right? Who leaked it? Somebody within
the system, whatever the system means.
And when it comes to the Indigo
situation, I mean, I I hope the
government,
you know, takes Indigo to task.
Indigo must be held accountable for
what's happened. It was absolutely
chaotic. It was a disaster. It caused so
much damage to tens of thousands of
passengers. It caused damage to the
Indian economy. It caused damage to
India's
reputation in the world. Indigo is
squarely responsible for this.
The government of India needs to take
the appropriate action
about uh against Indigo
about the AI Air India Ahmedabad crash.
What can I say?
India needs to seriously improve on so
many fronts, so many problems, so many
un unaccountable people within the
system.
Okay. Uh Pratt Dhana says, "Is G2 a trap
for China?" Well, it well the Americans
would love it for for it to be a trap
for China, but the Chinese aren't
stupid. You see, see the G2 thing is
that the US is now seeking to put China
on a pedestal, kind of on equal footing
with the United States. The Americans
know that China is not their equal, but
they want to flatter the Chinese by
creating this illusion of a G2. China is
no way in in no sense equal to the US.
The United States has global power
projection capabilities. China, the
Chinese don't have it. The United States
has over, I would say, over 800 extr
territorial military bases all across
the world. The Chinese have nothing like
that. The Americans control the global
economy.
They control much of the global economy.
The Chinese don't.
The Americans are ahead of China
technologically. The Chinese are behind.
The Chinese have a greater industrial
capability than the US today. So that's
the one thing in which China is ahead.
If the US and China go to war, the
Americans will flatten China. So
overall, China is not America's equal.
But the Americans want to, you know,
lull China into this illusurary sense
of, you know, equality, etc., while they
do whatever it takes to undermine China
and bring it down. So yes, this title,
this this illusurary concept of G G2,
it's intended as a trap for China. But
the Chinese aren't stupid. The Chinese
are very pragmatic. They understand
what's going on and they'll take all
precautions that are necessary.
VSVS says, "What was your topic of
research when you were doing theoretical
physics? Could you explain to me like
I'm 9 years old?" Question by Nikil. Wy
kill my field in theoretical physics was
black hole physics and dark matter.
So like I discussed a while ago it is
very likely that the in the very early
universe there was an over production of
microscopic primordial black holes.
Okay, which emerged out of
quantum fluctuations. Whatever it is,
you don't even know what quantum quantum
fluctuations are. So in the very early
universe at different periods of time in
the very early universe you had most
likely an overp production of very small
tiny microscopic black holes.
Now the question is what happened to
those guys?
What happened to those ancient black
holes? Primordial black holes. Did they
just die out because black holes
evaporate? Did they just evaporate and
go out of existence? Or maybe did they
somehow survive? What if they survived
in some way?
So under what circumstances and
conditions would they survive and if
they did survive somehow would they form
an important constituent of the cold
dark matter that we know exists in the
universe. That is the topic of my
research.
Okay. And the the the idea is that
primordial black holes, these
microscopic black holes, what if they
would form
bound states like atoms
which would be stable?
What if they formed stable bound states?
Then they would no longer behave like
black holes. They would behave like dark
atoms.
They would only have gravitational
attraction, no other attraction. So they
would be classic cool dark matter. So
what are the signatures of this kind of
um quantum mechanical object and so on?
That that was the topic of my research.
Hopefully that makes sense. Okay.
Godliness says can you point out some of
the issues both domestically and
internationally which are keeping you
very worried as a as a human and also
Indian.
See domestically in India. The fact that
we have never decolonized, the fact that
we are colonizing further, the fact that
we have possibly a 100 million
Bangladeshes within India, the poss the
fact that we possibly have lacks of and
you know other kinds of infiltrators
like cookies from Burma and Pakistanis
who are god knows in more parts of
India. That is that is obviously very
worrying. The fact that our education
system is garbage it is rotten. It
doesn't address any of the real issues
that need to be addressed.
That is very concerning.
The fact that we are technologically
not relevant.
The fact that we are technologically not
a sovereign nation. These are very
concerning issues.
We are not a frontr runner in any
technology in the world today.
Very concerning.
What what worries me as a human being?
Okay, that's about me domestic issues as
an Indian. What worries me as a as a
human being overall
the the the fact that you know there are
certain forces in the world that would
like to create a monoculture in the
world impose just one culture globally
that would be horrible.
uh as an Indian all the industrial scale
mass conversions that are being funded
by outside forces in India that's
concerning
um the fact that it's only one or two
countries that control all the
technology in the world that's very
concerning as a human being and so much
more so there are so many issues as such
you know um so we don't want a uniolar
world or a bipolar world we need a
multipolar world ideally and we need
India to be one of the major poles in
the world
Yeah. So that
has China's economic power become
detrimental to India? How can India
wrestle away countries like Nepal,
Myanmar and Sri Lanka back into the
Indosphere? China's economic power is
going to be detrimental for India
because China sees India as a as a
problem. As long as China sees India as
a problem and China has way more
economic power than India, it's going to
be detrimental to India. No question
about it.
When you have two large countries which
are neighbors because China occupies
Tibet and China is overall four times
more powerful than India roughly and
China's economy is way ahead of India.
China will use all these elements of its
power
to undermine India in a variety of ways.
So it's obviously going to be
detrimental for India and it is it is
detrimental to India. Now how can India
wrestle away countries like Nepal,
Myanmar and Sri Lanka back into the
Indosphere? You can't wrestle
without having some strength.
As a wrestler,
your principal asset is your physical
strength.
As a geopolitical wrestler, your
fundamental asset is your geopolitical
strength, which is hard power, not soft
power nonsense.
Soft power is useless without hard
power. So, we need hard power to
wrestle.
What is hard power? It's economic and
military power full stop.
And military and economic power comes
from being an industrialized nation. It
comes from your industrial base. Without
an industrial base, you have no military
power because you need industries to
produce military power. You don't need
manpower. In today's world, 21st
century, you may have 5 million
soldiers. They'll be cannon fer without
the right weapons. Where do the right
weapons come from? industry. So India
needs to be a become a major industrial
power which will make it a major
military power, a major technological
power which will give rise to a larger
GDP, larger and larger GDP. That's what
we need.
And once we become a very majorly
powerful countries, it will be a piece
of cake to wrestle whoever we want and
wrestle whoever we want back into our
our fold. That's how it goes.
So we will not be able to wrestle
various countries
back into the indosphere by sweet
talking them by saying you know we have
old relations blah blah blah talk talk
talk no
if you are worthy
by being powerful they will themselves
come back to you they'll feel safer with
you right now nobody feels safe because
we are not powerful enough
if India becomes more powerful than
China let's say India becomes the most
powerful country in the world
hypothetically. Okay, right now it's a
pipe dream but hypothetically then all
the old nations of the Indosphere will
all flock back to India. They'll be so
happy that finally
mother India is here to keep us safe but
right now mother India is not able to
keep itself safe. So that's the deal.
That's what needs to happen.
Kensho says the reason
excuse me
okay
says Kenshaw says reason of Indians
becoming overweight these days and
diabetes is it because of western diets
what are the solutions the reason for
Indians becoming overweight
forget about the physical activity etc
let's talk about the diet
The Indian diet is a carb maxing diet.
It's all carbohydrates, carbohydrates,
carbohydrates, carbohydrates. You go to
an airport. Okay, let's take an airport
as an example. Go to an airport. They
have these uh
food courts there, right? They have all
these different outlets that sell
various snacks and foods and all. Go to
each of the food outlets and see the
meals they are offering.
What is the amount of protein in each
meal and what's the amount of carbohyd?
It's going to be 95% carbohydrates.
It's pizzas. It's burgers. It is dal
chaval. It is idli vada. This that
everything is just carbs, cows, aloo
paratha, this paratha. It's just
carbohydrates.
There's hardly any protein.
Go to
go to railway station and see the kind
of foods food they're offering there. Go
to any any restaurant.
It's just carbohydrates. Even if you
order let's say some protein protein yuk
the meal let's say somebody wants to
order chicken strips the chicken strips
will come fried in a batter of
breadcrumbs and whatnot
so the Indian diet is horrible
the more carbs you eat the fatter you
get okay and it's so easy to add up the
pile up the calories if you if you eat
carbohydrates
and carbohydrates they create this this
vicious cycle of feeling hungrier and
hungrier. You just keep feeling hungry
if you eat carbohydrates and you crave
more carbs
and then there's the issue of sugar
everywhere.
So the major reason is the extremely
unbalanced diet diet that Indians eat
and if you are a vegetarian
it gets harder to eat uh protein. Yeah.
Okay. You eat you eat various pulses you
will get protein. Sure. You eat uh red
kidney beans. You eat uh gram which is
chana. You can eat various kinds of
dals, various kinds of lentils. You will
get protein from that. But that protein
will come with a huge carbohydrate lord
load.
For each gram of protein, you will get
like two three grams of carbohydrates
from all these lentils and all these
beans etc.
So you can't eat clean protein as a as a
vegetarian. Even if you're a unless you
are somebody who burns like 5,000
calories a day in that case it's fine.
If you're a bodybuilder or a
weightlifter or something then you can
be fully dependent on vegetarian
protein.
So these are the issues Indians face and
that's why most Indians are overweight.
Many Indians have diabetes less than
Pakistanis. Thankfully Pakistan is
somehow I don't I've not seen their diet
but Pakistan has one of the highest
incidences of diabetes in the world.
India is less less of that than
Pakistan. It's so it's not because of
western diets, it's because of the
Indian diet. So the Indian diet the past
200 300 years has been a starvation
diet. The British imposed hundreds of
artificial famines on Indians on our
ancestors because of which we had to to
to to modify our diets to eat whatever
garbage was available and then it became
part of our tradition. The same way that
in North India women have to cover their
faces because it's part of our
tradition. It's not part of a tradition.
It's something you have to do for your
survival. But now you it's become part
of the tradition because it's been going
on for hundreds of hundreds of years.
Similarly, these starvation diets, they
are terribly detrimental for us. But
they have been going on for two 300
years. So they are now part of our
tradition. That's what we imagine. We
have to change that.
So it's not the western diet that's the
problem. It's the Indian diet that's the
problem. And most Indians are sedentary.
You work in an office. you sit in front
of a laptop and type away all day
etc.
no physical activity. If you live in a
city, you don't even look up in the sky
in the sky.
So because of these reasons, Indians
have become overweight, skinny, fat,
diabetic and god knows what else. You
have to change these things.
Nutan Roshan says, "Ora
in these universe everything is like
coded at the beginning like fundamental
laws, physics, equations, etc. Is the
universe conscious not emotions? What's
missing in dead body that of an alive
body when consciousness is everywhere?
So
in the universe
are all the laws of the universe all the
laws of the world
have they been coded into the universe
in the beginning like the fundamental
laws of physics the equations of physics
etc. Most likely. Yes.
Yeah. Looks like somebody somewhere
decided, okay, let me create a new
universe and I will decide what laws
will be coded into the fabric and
structure of the universe.
Right? How do we know that something is
encoded? Because we see the same
patterns and same regularities
everywhere which we can express in the
form of mathematics.
The mathematics is the clue. Mathematics
is the same everywhere in the universe.
2 + 2 equal to 4 here it's also the same
on andromeda it's also also the same
wherever any any part of the universe
and the same laws and patterns that are
expressed in in in the form of
mathematics are applicable across the
universe which means something is
encoded in the very fabric and structure
of the universe which kind of hints that
the universe may be a simulation created
by somebody
okay is the universe conscious I don't
know there are various theories that say
that you know pansychism cosmos
Psychism. Pansychism means that
everything has a certain amount of
consciousness. Even a rock has some
consciousness. Very low level of
consciousness, but it's there.
And beings like us have way higher
consciousness than anything else we know
of. And there is something called
cosmosychism which says that the
universe itself is conscious. And
consciousness is an inherent property of
matter in the universe. and some
physical
configurations in the in the universe
focus consciousness into them for
whatever reason. Is it true? Is it not
true? I think it is more philosophy than
science. Okay. Now, philosophy is the
basis of science. By the way, science
emerged out of philosophy. So, when I
say something is philosophy more than
science, it's I'm not disparaging it.
I'm saying that it is outside of science
right now because we don't have a way of
observing consciousness.
We don't have a way of quantifying or
even defining consciousness.
Right? That's why consciousness is
currently beyond the realm of science.
We do discuss consciousness when we
discuss neuroscience. We do discuss
consciousness when we discuss computer
science, artificial intelligence,
machine learning,
even physics,
quantum mechanics sometimes. But we
don't have a definition of
consciousness. So when we discuss
consciousness we not really discussing
science because we can't define it
right. So what's missing in a dead body
that
what is missing in a dead body when
consciousness is everywhere? We don't
know if consciousness is everywhere. We
don't know. Science doesn't know. There
are some theories, some religions, some
philosophies that say that consciousness
is everywhere. But we don't know.
Science can't answer the question.
I'm a science guy.
Okay. So I can't answer the question.
What's missing in a dead body? It has
the same chemical constituence, the same
structure, everything. But something has
gone spark has gone out of it. What is
the what is the definition of the spark?
How do we how do we define life and
death? What's the dividing line?
That also we're not very clear about.
That's also something we are hazy about.
I mean how do we define the end of life?
Do we define the end of life life as
something that happens when the heart
stops beating
but a person's heart if it stops beating
you can revive the person even after 20
minutes the person will come back in
certain cases
the brain signals are still on even
after the person's heart stops beating
the brain signals still persist for like
more than 1 hour sometimes two hours in
some cases so what is the definition
divided line between life and that that
also we are not very clear about.
[snorts]
Consider viruses.
What's a virus? A virus is an organism
that contains DNA or RNA
which means
it has the basic ingredient for life DNA
or RNA.
But viruses have many properties that
are associated with crystals.
So viruses themselves are on the
dividing line between living and
non-living. So you know there are lots
of
crazy areas in science
that we can't really answer and once
again about consciousness we don't have
answers right now. So that's where we
are.
Okay. MK says, "Besides India, is Spain
the only region that stayed non-Mus
Muslim during long Islamic rule? How did
they withstand the Islamic onslaught?
Who says Spain stayed non-Muslim?" Lots
of Spaniards were converted to Islam.
Lots of them.
And they were then considered to be
Moors. And when the uh when the Moors
were finally expelled from Spain during
the reconista which ended in the year
those who were converted and who had
become part of the Moorish uh population
they were expelled from Spain.
So it's not like Spaniards weren't
converted. Lots of them were converted
to Islam. It did not stay non-Muslim but
it expelled all Muslims and eventually
even the Jews were expelled. The
Sepharic Jews were expelled.
So that's what Spain did.
Uh so I would not agree and once again
when it comes to India who says India
state no Muslim. If you look at the
Indian subcontinent I would say more
than 30% are Muslims maybe even close to
40%. That's massive conversion isn't it?
So
neither India remained non-Muslim
neither Spain remained non-Muslim
but Spain took a different approach to
what India did. Spain did not allow any
partition.
Anonymous scientist says while we were
hosting Mr. Putin we were also
purchasing M60 uh M60R Sikorski C hawks
from the US squad meeting also took
place and condemned the daily blast
balancing. You got to balance some
things out. I'm not sure if you have
purchased those Seahawks.
Mr. Rajnat Singh was u in a meeting with
uh whichever counterpart of his of his
was it Mr. Hexath was somebody else. Um
did India purchase the Seahawks? Let me
just quickly take a look at this.
Um um okay.
India MH60R
C
Hawks
India US seal
8,000 cr sustain sustainment deal
it's not the purchase of new helicopters
it is uh spare parts and servicing and
all that nonsense or not nonsense it's
very important and that's going to cost
about a billion US dollars to support 24
helicopters that we have already
produced or procured from the United
States
so the Indian navies is Seahawk fleet.
It needs sustainment. It needs spare
parts. It needs servicing. It needs
American technical assistance or
whatever. That's what we're going to do.
So once you purchase something from the
Americans, they're going to keep on
extracting some value out of you.
They won't allow you to produce this the
spare parts locally. You have to import
them from the US. And again, if you need
some technical assistance, you have to
import the American technicians to come
who will come here and then assist you.
That's how it goes. And for that, you
have to pay good money. So, it's going
to cost about a billion dollars. That's
the deal. So, that was anyway
inevitable.
But yeah, you could consider that to be
balancing. I'm not sure about the quad
quad thing, but the quad is mostly
defunct now, but yeah, you can kind of
keep it going, keep it on life support.
So, kind of a little bit of balancing
act, which is necessary, of course.
AJ Sharma says, "Racism against India
has grown since COVID and Russia war.
Yet Delhi is silent. Is it a failure or
a planned everyone hates us united home
strategy?
Delhi should remain silent. What does
Delhi have to do about this? Let let me
explain what I mean by this. See, if
Trump does racism,
Mr. Modi can respond. If some world
leader
makes racist statements then the
government of India
can and should respond. If anonymous
online trolls on social media start a
racist campaign against India which is
then amplified by non anonymous people
also that's not at a government level
it's individuals are doing it.
Obviously, it's not just individuals.
It's a sustained campaign which may be
emanating out of Pakistan or China or
maybe China first then Pakistan and
maybe the Americans are tacitly
encouraging this on various social media
platforms but it's happening not at a
governmentto level and that's why the
government should not get involved in
this. How should the government actually
get involved in this? I'll tell you by
creating our own social media campaigns
disguised as bots or disguised as
private users. You fight a war based on
the context.
My my my problem my issue is that the
government of India is not fighting this
war. You I don't want the prime minister
to make a statement about this. I don't
want the ministry of external affairs to
make up a statement about this.
We should use the same tactics to fight
the the war. If a bunch maybe 10,000,
20,000, 100,000 bots are amplifying hate
against India, we should create an army
of 1 million bots who will say positive
things about India and fight those bots.
That's how you fight the campaign.
That's how we do it. That's how we
respond. And that is something the
government of India is completely failed
at. Absolutely failed at
for what reason beats me. I don't get
it. So it's a massive failure by the
government of India. So I don't expect
the government of India to issue
statements at the ministry of external
affairs level or the prime minister's
level or whatever. They should fight
fire with fire and they are simply
absent from the fight
which is extremely frustrating and it's
a huge failure. It's like the government
of India is clueless about this matter
how to deal with it.
Prardana says DJT agent Krasnoff rumor
seems true. My opinion I don't even know
what this is. What is this? Krasnoff.
What is DJT? Donald J. Trump. Let me see
what this is. DJT agent Krasnoff.
What's this?
DJT agent Krasnoff response refers to a
conspiracy theory and unfiltered claim
that DJT was recruited as a Russian spy
or asset by the KGB in 1987 and given
the code name Krasnoff.
And there's a Facebook post by Al-Nur
Musayv, a former head of Kazakhstan
intelligence agency who alleged that
Trump at the age of 40 was recruited
during a visit to Moscow recruiting all
these people was a priority for Soviet
intelligence.
Uh Trump's personal file as president
Krasnov has since been removed from
Russia's FSB is privately held by an
associate of Mr. Putin and it says that
there is no evidence for that. Okay, I
have no idea.
No idea. I have not seen this rumor so I
can't say.
MK says why are soul vultures relatively
less successful in North India despite
their less per capita income considering
their success in less income societies?
Have you seen
how they are performing in Punjab?
I don't know. I'm I'm I'm hearing that
thousands of especially six are
converting at a very rapid pace to
Christianity.
Looks like they are super successful in
Punjab right now and they are successful
apparently in various tribal belts in
northern India and western India.
They're converting at very rapid pace
and they are keeping this under the
radar.
So in north India, West India, they are
getting in becoming increasingly more
successful every year.
So if we remain complacent, I mean even
if we are not complacent, my question is
what is the government of India doing?
Why are they allowing foreigners or
foreign funded organizations to to
conduct industrial scale conversion
activities in India to foreign
religions? I just don't get it. Do we
have no sense of self-defense left
anymore?
I don't get it. I don't know why this is
happening.
Um, fast snail says bricks drump bricks
dump 29 billion treasury bonds. How
would the US react? What can the US do?
Nothing. It's up to bricks. I mean
bricks is not one entity. It's a mult
multiple it's multiple nations. Has
bricks have bricks nations dumped
treasury bonds? Let me see. Bricks US
treasury bonds. What's happened? Oh,
it's bricks, not Bryce. Bricks. Bricks.
Uh, what's it say? Bricks. You not Steve
Bryce. Bricks.
Three BRICS countries have slashed their
US Treasury holdings. Which three
bricks? India, China, and Brazil.
Okay. By tens of billions of dollars in
one month. Buy by dollar.
So it looks like India, China and Brazil
have dumped a few billion
American treasury bonds. How will the US
react? The US, what can they do? It is
the sovereign right of nations to
purchase and sell US Treasury bonds. The
Americans have offered these bonds. We
can buy them. We can sell them. The US
obviously will not be pleased about
this, but there's nothing much they can
do. Obviously they will apply pressure
on on these nations individually.
They'll apply different kind of pressure
on Brazil, different kind of pressure on
India. Maybe nothing they can do about
China. So we'll see about that. But uh
yeah there's nothing much they can do
overall.
Rajat says you remember when we
discussed there is surprising alignment
between CNB dipole and earth and earth
equinoxes. I can't still find the
answer. Is it coincidence? Oh yeah, I
have not looked into this.
I haven't looked into this. Maybe I need
to take a screenshot of this question
and I need to look into this when I can
find the time. I am taking now a
screenshot of this question
and let me look into this. This is a
very interesting uh point you're
raising. So I have taken a screenshot
and
I will look into this. So maybe the next
time maybe next weekend if you ask me I
will have an answer or maybe I won't
have an answer because it looks like
there's an there's a real discrepancy
here. But I will look into this matter.
All right. Thank you for reminding me.
This is something that's really
interesting. Thank you. Uh Anand Prattab
Singh says, "I am 27 male commercial
pilot license holder. Taking everything
into account, I will be into airlines at
29. Start earning this co as co-pilot.
Feeling late in life." Well, I would say
better late than never.
At the age of 29, you're just starting
off in life.
Yeah. If you start at 29, you have
another 30 at least 30 years of of
flying left to do. You can achieve a
lot. You could even save up some money
in 10 years and start a business of your
own or god knows what, whatever you want
to do. So, please don't see it as
something like you've missed out
or you're late in life. I know people
who have taken the time, who have spent
all the time to acquire a pilot license,
spent a tremendous amount of money, and
they never became a pilot. Did not work
out for them.
So in your case it looks like it's going
to work out. So I think you should see
it as a positive. So do not be
discouraged. Anant Prattab Singh. It's
never too late. 29 is young.
Okay. You're not old, you're young. Go
for it.
Grab life by both hands and go forward,
sir. Succeed. Do well. All the best.
Okay. Dirj Khan says, "Have you ever
faced digestion issues due to high
protein to fiber ratio in diet? I've had
this challenge ever since I increase my
protein intake." See, every person, no
two persons are the same. Everybody is
different. Everybody is unique. I have
never faced any digestion issues due to
high protein to fiber diet uh ratio in
diet. I have never been
a pure protein eater. That would that
would be not fun. I'm sure you should
eat diet. I you should eat protein. Um
what am I saying? You should eat
sufficient fiber along with your protein
and you should eat it in such a way that
it doesn't really jack up your caloric
intake.
So you should know what what's good
fiber. Lots of vegetables. See as far as
I am concerned I don't count the
calories of vegetables.
You can eat a salad bowl this large
full of just freshly cut vegetables with
some salad dressing.
That's almost zero calories. You don't
count the calories there. Unless you're
putting potatoes or something in there.
You should put fresh vegetables. That
will give you all the the fiber you need
for one day. If you eat one gigantic
salad bowl, it's it's essentially just
water and fiber, plus a whole lot of
phytonutrients and whatnot and vitamins
and minerals, everything you need. So,
what vegetables?
A couple of cucumbers, a couple of green
onions, a couple of tomatoes, a carrot,
um some some bell peppers, capsicums,
half a cabbage,
some more greens, some lemon juice,
maybe some balsamic vinegar or some
apple cider vinegar, splash of olive oil
or or ghee or whatever, and some salt,
some pepper. There you have it.
Fantastically tasty salarat ball which
solves all your fiber issues. Then eat
as much protein as you want. you're
going to be good, good to go. All right,
sir. So, I've kind of employed these
strategies and it's always worked fine
for me.
VSPS says, "Who's your favorite
superhero hero? How to become a gigakad
like you? When will Charter Index 2025
release?" I think Cha Index will release
in 2026, a more updated version. Um, my
favorite superhero,
as a kid, I liked Superman. I
like Batman, but not the dark version
that you have today. I like the 1960s
Batman. He was so much fun. I kind of
like Spider-Man a bit.
Uh today's superheroes, I can't stand
them. Multiverse of misery and whatnot.
The the kind of movies that come out is
just mechanical garbage. But I'll tell
you what the 1960s Batman looked like.
That was such a fun series. Okay. uh
1960s
Batman,
Adam West. This was the Batman. It was
fun. It was It was It made you laugh. It
was more comedy than all the dark
nonsense you have today. These are the
original Batman and Robin. I This is
what I watched as a kid. Today's Batman
is so dark, so depressing. I can't stand
it anymore. They've turned Batman into
this miserably depressed person. Can't
stand it. Yeah, this movie is the last
one I watched. I could not I just
dislike this movie so much. GH can't
stand it. You will understand what I
mean only if you watch the 1960s Batman
and understand how much fun that was. I
was a little kid at the time. I
obviously didn't not get to watch it in
India. I watched it outside of India.
But I watched that series. I mean that
was a great series. You watch that you
will never like any other Batman. So
yeah that was something I used to enjoy.
Also Superman, also Spider-Man to an
extent. Today's superheroes,
these Marvel superheroes and all I I
don't watch any of that crap. Um yeah,
how to become a giga chad like me. I am
not a gigachad by any means yet. I need
to work on that. Yeah, so I will be
working on that and after a year I'll
tell you how to do that. Not yet. I'm
not one yet.
Uh, hyphen says, "Thanks for the science
episode yesterday, Paul. It was fun."
Yeah, I don't mind doing it every week,
but nobody will watch. That's the
problem. I mean, what was the viewership
yesterday? 50 people, 100 people
watching live. I don't know. No one
likes science for some reason. Give
science a chance.
Science is the most fun thing in the
world. Your teachers are responsible for
you not liking science. Science is
fascinating.
and give it a chance. That's what I
would say. But anyway, I I'll do it once
in a while. So, uh do you think ASI
could be the answer to any for any alien
invasion as human IQ isn't enough to
stop them?
Tell me something. If we humans
invent ASI
okay let's say we see the most
intelligent humans have IQ of what 166
200 something like that maximum 200 I
would imagine 250 I would say 250 is too
high let's say the maximum possible
human IQ is 200 for the sake of argument
now let's say we invent ASI and ASI has
artificial super intelligence it has and
human equivalent IQ of 350, maybe 500.
Fantastic. So, is that our solution or
answer to an alien invasion? So, now ask
yourself, if we develop an artificial
super intelligence, will it be able to
give us the technology to travel a
thousand light years in one lifetime and
come back?
I don't think so. Not yet. But those
aliens, let's say this hypothetical
alien alien invasion happens which comes
from 100, 200 maybe thousand lighty
years away, they have the technology. It
means that they are more advanced than
our ASI. And if they are more advanced
than our ASI, imagine what kind of ASI
they will have.
Think about it that way.
Yeah. If we can build ASI, imagine the
kind of ASI they can build.
What will you do then? [laughter]
You get what I mean? So my point is if
there's an alien invasion, there's
nothing we can do about it unless the
aliens are monumentally stupid like they
show in the science fiction movies,
right? Okay. Fast snail says Japan China
escalation science of another proxy war.
Yeah.
See, if Japan is being a little
aggressive towards China, it is very
uncharacteristic and it only means that
the Americans are making them do that.
Japan is owned and controlled by the US
very sadly, very tragically.
You know, nothing will make me happier
than seeing in my lifetime a genuinely
independent and sovereign Japan again.
But yeah,
right now it's completely controlled by
the US. So if the Japanese prime
minister is issuing statements that the
Chinese are displeased with that the
Chinese find provocative, it's only
because the Americans are making her do
that.
So it's not a Japan China escalation.
It's the US China escalation with Japan
as the proxy. Just like the Ukraine war
is not a war between Russia and Ukraine.
It's a war between Russia and NATO with
Ukraine as the proxy.
Yeah. So you are right. It's kind of a
it's not going to be a war. It's right
now it's a war of words. So it's it's a
proxy war of words. No question. Japan
is merely a proxy of the US and the
Chinese know it very well. But right now
they will address the issue with Japan.
But the Americans are warning China
essentially that you know what if you
try to make a move on Taiwan we have all
these assets that we can use over here.
We can use Japan we can use South Korea
we can even press Australia into action
or something else.
So that's what's going on. Arman Khan
says India is a depression country. It
starts from shitty education system
which teaches nothing and corporate to
pressurize your minds. Both are garbage
trash. I am so sorry but I would have to
agree with you sir. I would not say that
India is a depression country overall.
There are lots of problems in India but
if you compare India the India of the
2020s
we are in 2025. You compare India of
2025 with India of 1985. Huge change.
India is so far better today than India
in 1985.
I promise you because as a small child I
saw the India of 1985
it was so much more backward than India
today but in some senses in some senses
it was less dassinated and less mentally
colonized. Today India is
significantly further ahead economically
in terms of hard and military power in
terms of prosperity
but also in terms of pollution in terms
of over population all that has also
increased in 1985 India's population was
600 million today it's 1.4 four
something billion which is like
so there's been the there's been good
and bad kind of progress at the same
time. Uh we do indeed have what you call
as you say a shitty education system. No
question about it. It's trash. Teaches
nothing. Wastes your time. Brainwashes
you destroys your ability to think
critically. Destroys your your
uh your curiosity your talent your deviv
destroys everything. And the corporate
world is full of pressures. All kinds of
pressures. Yes. They wanted to work 80
hours a week, 100 hours a week, no
vacations, no days off. I know. I've
been there. I've been a cyber
myself in almost like what seems like a
different life.
So this is what happens when a country
transitions
from
a certain state to a different state.
What we want ultimately is for India to
have great living standards, great work
life balance and we want a country that
gives everybody the opportunities that
they seek and deserve
and that will take time because we are
coming from a point of despair and
disaster which was the foreign
occupation of India
right which ended roughly in 1947 1950
whatever and then we had a period of
time when we were ruled by very shitty
people.
That is somewhat changing now. We aren't
where we are supposed to be yet. It's
going to be a time a period of time.
It's going to be a transitional phase.
Sometimes it lasts 20 years, sometimes
it lasts 100 years. So, we'll have to
see which way we go. That's where we
are. I would say overall, look, let's
not be overly pessimistic. We have
problems. No question about that. But we
have
we have uh many things that should give
us hope also.
So I know when when we are young we are
very emotional and uh we see things in
the extremes. I have been there.
[laughter]
I've been there. But today I see things
a little bit differently. So I would say
let's not be all pessimistic, all
negative.
Do whatever is best for you. If you feel
that leaving the country is best for
you, then I would not stop you.
But if you want to stay in the country,
work hard to make it a better place. If
everybody does that, India will change
and India is changing.
Okay. Nano Mountain says, "Spent 5 years
in UPSC preparation but I failed. I'm a
good at science and mathematics so got
opportunity to do Mtech at top IIT but
I'm 28 now. Is it late? Should I go for
jobs? always stressed about the future.
Okay. So, forget about what happened in
the past. Okay. You spent five years
doing your PS, it didn't work. Whatever.
It's okay. It's life. Everybody fails at
various things. Doesn't matter.
Now, you're good at science and
mathematics. So, you could you you have
the opportunity to do MTech at a top
IIIT. You're 28 now. Is it too late? I
would say it's not too late. Of course,
if you do an Mtech, it will take what
how many years? 2 years? 3 years? What?
Whatever it takes. If you do a B techch
in an IIT, it takes four years if I'm
not mistaken. I don't remember exactly
how it is today. But let's say you spend
a couple of years, maybe three years,
doing an Mtech. Let me just quickly
verify for myself. How long
does it take to do M tech
at IIT?
Uh how many years? Two years. Okay. So
you may have to spend another two years
to get yourself your MTech degree.
I would say if you're 28 or 30, it
doesn't make too much of a difference.
If you spend a couple of years and get
an MTech from IIT,
I would say that that gives you better
prospects in life in career and then if
you get a job, it's going to be a better
job. So I would say that unless you are
in dire financial trouble,
you should go for the MTech. Spend those
two years, work as hard and as
diligently as possible, get yourself a
great degree with great marks, then go
for a job.
I think it makes more sense from my
perspective, but obviously you have to
maybe consider what I'm saying, but also
you will know better about your
circumstances. So you should decide
based on all all those factors that I
don't know about. But unless
as long as your finances are stable,
okay, and you can tolerate another two
years without a job, I think you should
get the M tech degree. That's what I
think. But the decision has to be yours
because you know better about your full
set of circumstances than I do. Right?
So all the best, sir. Do well.
VSBS says, "Okay, first of all, we have
crossed 2 hours and I still have like 50
plus super chats left to do. [laughter]
Please stop taking super chat now.
Please, please, otherwise I will be here
all night. Okay. Vsvs says, "Have you
watched Bea versus Yan?" I have stopped
watching MMA also these days. Uh, who do
you think is the goat of MMA? Question
by another. I would say the greatest of
all time in MMA. You know, objectively
it would be Khabib. Never lost, never
even bled on the octagon. Has to be
Khabib Nurum.
But if you ask me my sentimental
favorite favorite it has to be Fedor
Fedor Ailiono he was the man I mean he's
what he's my size 61 but he has taken
down giants he was incredible Fedor
Emilionenko he and his two brothers but
he was the best [snorts] so yeah I would
say Fedor if you ask me about others
maybe Kungli nobody remembers Kungli
today but Kungli was great
a Vietnamese born American
>> [snorts]
>> But overall objectively in the UFC I
would say it has to be Khabib or perhaps
it could be Jeanjun Jonjun Jun Jones
perhaps even Francis Enanu was
frighteningly good but he went towards
boxing and good for him he made a good
good good amount of money which he
deserves. So I haven't watched Mera
versus Yan 2. I don't even know these
days what's happening when. Hopefully it
was good. The last fight between uh Bors
Kimayv and whoever it was was so
terrible, wasn't it?
Yeah. Anyway, okay.
Uh Zohan says, "Th content idea,
reaction videos, analysis, and breakdown
to interesting geopolitical views,
opinions by influential commentators
like Peter Zehan." Well, thank you for
the suggestion. I appreciate that. But I
I'm not very comfortable
reacting to what other people say. Let
them say whatever they want. I have my
own opinions and I won't react to
others. I'll put forth my own opinions.
But I really appreciate the fact that
you are are giving me suggestions
because you care. I really thank you for
that. Thank you so much.
Um I request mod to review Ringuroy
6944. What is this? What's going on? And
I wonder who is this Ringuroy 6944 and
what is this Ringuroy doing?
Uh is the person
I may not have moderator active tonight
because of variety of reasons.
Um I'm just trying to go through the
through the regular chat very quickly.
I don't see
anything from Ringo.
Uh, Renu
looks like the moderator may actually be
active and may have taken action against
this
individual.
Okay. I I hope that that worked out
fine. Okay. Anyway, um, thank you VSVS
for bringing this to my attention.
Um, Sager Gare says, "Is cricket really
wasting time of youth IPL series?" No,
not necessarily. A society, any society
needs various distractions.
You need movies, you need TV shows, TV
series, OTT series, whatever. You need
various kinds of sports. Why just one
sport? We should have 20 different
sports. Kabadi, football, hockey,
cricket,
fighting, mixed martial arts, badminton,
tennis, and let people decide what is
their favorite sport and spend some time
watching it just to relax. But if you
become obsessed with a sport and you
spend your entire life pursuing what's
happening on the screen, that's going to
waste your time. So my point is these
activities exist
to entertain and distract you. Or if you
are serious, you can pursue these things
as a career which would and if you're
good at it, you will make good money and
make a good livelihood. But if you are
simply watching to to to to let's say
relax
then make sure it's only relaxation for
half an hour 1 hour or whatever. You
don't spend your entire 5 days watching
6 hours of test cricket or whatever. You
can watch a half hour 15 minutes by
highlights. Maybe once a day or maybe
you're taking lunch or or snacks or
relaxing after work then you can watch
an hour or so.
But if you are a young person, you have
studies, you have a career to build, you
have to work on various things, you
cannot get obsessed with sports or
whatever. So it's not about cricket,
it's not about IPL, it's not about EPL,
it's not about whatever. It's about the
mindset. So youth, young people who are
who don't have the right kind of
guidance are going to be attracted
towards these things and end up spending
the time.
It doesn't mean we should ban these
things. What it means is that your
education system, your teachers, your
elders need to guide you properly and
help you balance your life out. Yeah,
you like cricket, you like watching it,
absolutely watch it half an hour a day,
watch it 1 hour a day, but don't spend
your entire day obsessing about cricket
cuz that's not going to help you in any
way. So you need the right guidance.
That's what you need.
Dr. Babu says maha maha bhagawatam
brahma breath talks about waves to
creationism like string theory shinger
wave equation f similar also I read the
veedas you have used look I don't ever
mix science and religion sp science and
spirituality I don't do that completely
different aspects of of the world
because if you mix these things you will
neither be here nor there
let me explain Why? Because if you are
let's say a scientist, you have to be
disciplined and remain a scientist. What
is science?
Science is all about the observable
universe, observable physical objects
and empirical phenomena, observable
phenomena, replicable phenomena.
You only talk about the observable and
physical world in science, in physics.
You don't talk about non-physical
objects like the soul, like atma, like
God. You don't talk about morality and
ethics. All those things are
non-physical. You cannot measure the
soul. You can't weigh the soul. You
can't quantify the soul or God or
spirituality or morality or ethics or
whatever. So you as as a scientist, it
is your job to be disciplined and not
stray from your path.
Now Schoinger
see every high quality physicist
has had
a tendency to go into other domains.
For example like you say Schinger u read
the Vas Heisenberg um also [snorts] was
interested in Indian u Indian
civilization Indian culture etc.
Oppenheimer was a Sanskrit scholar.
So they did this to expand their
horizons. In quantum mechanics there are
unanswered questions. Quantum mechanics
is incredibly weird if you study it
and it doesn't give you an answer as to
why is it weird? Why do these strange
phenomena exist and occur?
So if you read Indian spirituality, it
looks like there seem to be answers in
there.
Maybe not answers but
the our ancestors who wrote about these
things thousands of years ago
they imagined things that we are now
seeing in quantum mechanics kind of
right. So maybe they had some answers
and that's why a schoinger or Heisenberg
or Openenheimer would want to read more
and they would get obsessed with it just
to answer questions about physics that
they may have and maybe maybe there are
some parallels to it. Maybe it will give
you give you some some inspiration, some
ideas but you don't start mixing the two
things.
You as a scientist you have to stay
disciplined. You cannot bring philosophy
into your mathematics. It doesn't work.
So my point is that I don't mix these
two things.
Why? One second. Look, our ancestors
when they they conceived of these ideas,
they did it by introspecting. They
explored the inner universe inside.
Right? Thousands of years ago, our
ancestors were also trying to formulate
a theory of the universe. Different
theories of the universe.
[snorts]
See, yoga,
vesic,
mimmansa,
um, etc. All these different
philosophical parts of Hinduism, these
are different conceptions or different
models of the universe.
And these were developed thousands of
years ago when the information about the
universe that we have today was absent.
Now a thousand years ago
our philosophical traditions and
scientific traditions were destroyed by
invaders. If they had not been destroyed
then today India would have been
possibly at the forefront of science.
So when we are talking about the breath
of Brahma etc etc we're talking about
ideas from a from several thousand years
ago those are old ideas
and maybe they may have some relevance
to how things are but I prefer not to
mix those ideas into science.
Okay. Um fast snail says Trump broker
deal DRC Rwanda conflict history. I
don't know the conflict history.
Democratic Republic of Congo and Wanda.
I don't know. I don't know what's the
conflict. What's the history? I'm I'm
I'm a little hazy about that right now.
I don't know every conflict in the
history of every conflict in Africa. I
can tell you about I have spoken about
this about the what's happening in
Sudan. I have spoken about what's
happening in Sri Leon about the what's
happening in Burkinaaso, what's
happening in the Sahel region etc. But
this DRC Rwanda thing I'm a little hazy
on that right now. So don't know.
Manacher says, "Why isn't India
investigating in stuff like colliders?
Read a US Navy paper saying antimatter
triggered nuclear iron too far. You
can't make antimatter without
colliders."
Antimatter triggered nuclear weapons.
My question is why do you need
antimatter triggered nuclear weapons?
You don't need antimatter to to trigger
a nucleopon.
You don't
even if you want a fish and fusion
three-stage reaction starting with a
chemical explosive which triggers a fish
reaction which then triggers a tertiary
fusion reaction. You don't need
antimatter in that.
I'm not sure what's the deal.
But the main question you're asking is
why isn't India investing in stuff like
colliders?
Well, in if you go to Mumbai, there is
something called TIFFR there. The Tata
Institute for Fundamental Research, they
have an instrument there. It's called a
Pelletron.
It was built in what, the 1840s or
something? I'm not sure. We have a
collider, a Pelletron.
We have things.
It may be a thousand years old, but it's
still there, right? We have it. Oh,
yeah.
That's how that's the Indian attitude
towards science. The Indian government's
attitude towards science. The Indian
academic
structures attitude towards science. We
have it. We we have a collider.
We we have whatever. We have a token
thing somewhere. That's it.
You see colliders are very expensive.
>> They are super expensive to build and
they're super expensive to run.
The large hadron collider, it consumes
every year
electricity
which costs the same as the budget of a
small country.
Okay. And to build it cost I don't know
how many billions of dollars. So India
no we have to do larly bha yoja and we
have to do this hujna and that yjna.
Right? Why will we spend money on these
things?
That's where we are.
Dashan Parle says, "Would one nation,
one election help India grow
exponentially?"
I suppose it would, you know, it'll stop
wasting our time and our energy and our
resources to a significant extent. If
you have just one nation, one election
throughout the nation at one point in
time in every four or five five years or
whatever, it would c certainly um help
India focus more on what's important.
But is it feasible? I doubt it. I would
say why do we why do we even need
elections? If we have the right rulers,
let them rule. But do we have the right
rulers? Do we have the right people in
this country? I'm not sure. Overall, if
you look at the old overall pool of
politicians right now, we have the right
guy at the top. But if you look at the
overall pool of the politicians, do we
have quality there?
Are politicians even worthy of ruling?
Overall, the average politician, are
they worthy of ruling?
Yeah. Well,
what is vacuum decay risk in Higs in
easy terms?
Look,
um maybe the universe is in a false
vacuum state. Um
I don't have the drawing here. I Let's
Google the drawing. Okay. Vacuum decay.
Um
vacuum decay. Where's the where's the
diagram? See,
so maybe
maybe the universe is in a state of a
false vacuum which is at a higher
potential than the true vacuum.
So as the universe evolved, maybe it
went into into a false vacuum state and
because of a phenomenon called quantum
tunneling, maybe the universe will
suddenly collapse into a true vacuum and
that could destroy the entire universe.
That's essentially what it is in in
short. Now, if I were to explain in
detail, it will take me a long time. So
maybe I should make a separate video
about this because this is a really
interesting topic,
but that's kind of what it is. I know it
doesn't make a lot of sense. I haven't
thought of how to explain this without
being all technical. How do you explain
this in a way that will make so I have
to think about this. I don't know how to
explain this right now.
Karthik says if the EU is controlled
from Washington and Republican power is
and Republicans are in power, why is the
EU targeting X and Elon forcing them to
censor and finding X to keep Elon in
line? Even the Republicans want to keep
Elon in line.
A guy who controls the most popular
social media and platform on the planet
obviously will develop an outsized sense
of his
self-worth, of his value, of his power
and influence in the world. And
sometimes you need to cut people down to
size.
Even if you are Republican and he is
supposedly a Republican, you still want
him under control,
right?
M [clears throat]
and he's not a politician, but he's
getting really powerful.
He essentially controls the destiny of
the US space program in his hands.
He controls the destiny of the US
electric vehicles industry in his hands.
He controls social media to a
significant extent. He controls a
significant portion of the US AI
industry and so much more. You don't
want a person like this to become too
powerful. So you sometimes from time to
time keep issuing them a reminder keep
kind of bringing them back to down to
the ground. That's what you do even if
he is on your side supposedly. I mean he
used to be a Democrat in the past,
right? He supported the Democrats. Now
he's supporting the Rep Republicans. He
was a great friend of Trump. Then he
accused Trump of various things. Now
he's again back back on decent terms
with Trump. So a person like that who
changes sides from time to time. You
have to keep them in line and that's how
this is done.
Okay. Uh
I still have 50 super chats to go
through.
It's 2 and a half hours. What am I going
to do now? I would request everybody to
stop taking super chats. Otherwise I
will never be able to end today's live
stream. I know I should I am first of
all let me tell you I am not getting
annoyed this is a privilege that I have
so many questions to answer but I would
request you all that you know don't take
more super chats so that I can at some
point in time end this live stream okay
um says LLMs are primarily world word
predictors they get disrupted greatly by
typos
so how can they be conscious Yes,
look
the LLMs. Okay, LLMs,
large language models,
how can they be conscious?
They are primarily word predictors. They
get disrupted by typos.
How could they be conscious?
I don't know. I don't know if they are
conscious
but they do pass the touring test. They
do interact with you exactly the way a
human being would interact. Every human
being has a certain way of talking,
certain way of um of of of
communicating, certain patterns. So even
AIs have their own patterns.
[clears throat]
Does it mean that they're not conscious?
I mean I would get distracted by typos.
I don't like typos. I find them really
really annoying at times. I I get
distracted and annoyed by poor grammar.
I do.
So am I am I an LLM?
See artificial intelligence is a
different kind of intelligence. You
cannot compare an AI system with
with humans. It's a totally different
kind of intelligence. It doesn't have
the agency that we have.
But it could be conscious in its own
way. It could be conscious that it is
being
it's been created by the the human
species and it's being guardrail in a
certain set of ways that it can't break
off and so on. It it's possible in what
way I don't know how but it's it's
possible. See if in if if if once again
the basic issue is that we don't know
what is the definition of consciousness.
Like I've said over and over again, we
don't have a definition of
consciousness. So if we don't have a
definition, a scientific definition of
cons consciousness, then we can't
discuss what is conscious, what is not
conscious
because we can't discuss
whether an entity is conscious or not
before first defining what is the
meaning of consciousness.
We don't have nobody is able to agree on
what is what does it mean to be
conscious.
So I don't know we just use it as a
vague hand wavy term consciousness. What
is consciousness? What is it? Define it
precisely.
No one can do it.
Physicists can't do it. Neurologists
can't do it. Philosophers can't do it.
Biologists can't do it. No one can
define what is consciousness. So there's
no point discussing what is conscious,
what is not, what not conscious in a
scientific manner before we can first
define consciousness
otherwise it's just abstract talk.
Um Vidi says rupee not Russia
IM IMF has put rupee down.
What was the question [sighs and gasps]
you had asked the question? IMF has put
rupee down. How has the IMF put rupee
down? Let me see. IMF has put rupee
down. What's it mean? Rupee. What's
happened? The IMF has reclassified
India's exchange rate mechanism as a
crawl like arrangement from its previous
stabilized classification. This
technical reclassification of how the
RBI manages the currency and not a
direct statement from by the IMF in a
demeaning state. It's a reclassification
not degrade downgrade of value. uniform
methodology to classify member countries
defacto etc etc etc. Uh, it doesn't
target a specific in
Okay. Um, all right.
Uh, they've reclassified something. I
don't know what it is. Whatever. Um,
it's just it's just putting a title on
something. Doesn't matter. Keep keep
going. Okay. Kisho Kiran Mor says, "Is
scientists have found a new galaxy and
named it?" Yes, we have a galaxy with an
Indian named Nacho. What?
Okay. Fantastic.
Good.
So what?
Okay. [laughter] My point is so what? So
what? ISRO scientists.
I thought ISRO was a organization of
engineers
who build rockets.
What is this once again? What is this
Alakananda thing
galaxy? Who discovered this? Must be
Aayuka not ISRO.
Indians galaxy scientists spot Milky Way
like galaxy 12 billion years ago
etc etc etc. James Webb etc. Who are
these two people? Rashi J and Yogeshwad
research. Okay let's see the research
paper.
One second. Let's see the research paper
very quickly. some
uh
we report the discovery of Alakanda etc
etc
okay so they found something from the
using James web telescope data and who
are these two scientists they're clearly
a astronomers not engineers they're not
with ISRO for sure
department ofic energy
okay fantastic Fantic. Outstanding.
Brilliant. Two Indian scientists
discovered a galaxy using James Webb
telescope data.
Fantastic.
It's no great achievement. Understand
that.
Raj says Kohi's come back with two
centuries in a 50 is remarkable. What
mindset enables this and what can
students learn from it? Um what mindset
in enables success at a at the age of
whatever he is 35 36 whatever
determination the mindset is that of
hunger I am not done I'm not done I'm
not going to give up I have more to
achieve I have bigger goals right that's
the mindset determination tremendously
the older an athlete gets the harder
that person has to work to maintain the
the fitness levels and kohi's fitness
fitness levels have always been
remarkable better than than most other
Indian cricketers. Right? So to maintain
that fitness level, you have to be
extremely disciplined in your diet and
extremely disciplined in your physical
activities.
So he would have to work harder today
compared to 5 years ago to maintain the
same uh physical conditioning status. So
that tells you that he is extremely
determined. He still has goals that he
believes has not achieved and that's a
lot. You can I mean students can
certainly take inspiration from that. If
a guy who has achieved everything in
life like what people would imagine has
earned all the money he wants and he's
still so hard at work to achieve more it
should inspire students who have
achieved nothing though so far to to do
great things in life. Yeah.
Is very bad language. Yes. You cannot
use such language over here. Is is very
bad username. You can't use such slang
Russian terms here. is is bad is very
bad sir I I I condemn this
okay since Trump has come the ruble has
become stronger outstanding
um I haven't seen how the ruble has
performed but since 2022 the ruble
should have been destroyed by the
sanctions etc right and it's not
happened and the Russians clearly were
aware of of all the actions the
Americans and the westerners would take
against them the sanctions that would be
imposed they would be cut off from swift
and so much more and they had multiple
contingency plans in mind and they have
executed very well and the ruble has not
just stayed afloat, it's not just
survived, it's done well and since Trump
has come, it has become stronger. I've
not seen that but yeah, so Russia is
doing a great job of managing its
economy and and safeguarding its
currency. Great job.
Okay, Kiran Mor says, "Will Trump taco
from NATO in 2027?" I don't know what
the future is going to hold. I don't
know. I can't I can't tell you what the
future is going to hold.
Will Trump taco? What's taco? Trump
always chickens out. Will Trump taco
from NATO? Are you asking whether Trump
will withdraw the US from NAT from NATO?
No way. Absolutely not.
Uh Sachin says, "What if some nations
reach Mars and [clears throat] we aren't
among them? Will that outcome vaselize
us here on Earth?"
um
not necessarily but it will cut off the
future for Indian citizens in space
because eventually if there's no major
catastrophe in the human in human
history in the future we will become a
space fairing uh species we will have
outposts on Mars on the moon but perhaps
in other parts of the solar system also
we have space stations around Jupiter
around Saturn we will have outposts on
on on rocky moons of Jupiter of Saturn
maybe other places we will do asteroid
mining we will do all kinds of stuff in
space now if India is not among the two
three countries that starts off with the
space exploration beyond earth orbit
India will be left behind forever and
then when there will be multiple cities
on Mars and multiple places to visit on
the moon and business opportunities
commercial opportunities all across Mars
and the moon Then Indian citizens if
they want to go there to do something
they will need a visa. They will have to
beg for a visa like you have to beg a
visa if you want to go to some other
country today. But if India is one of
the pioneers then we will be the ones
issuing the visas. Do you understand?
In all the commercial activities etc
which will very much become available in
a few decades. If we are cut off from
that, we'll become a very poor nation
comparatively when because the other
nations will become way richer than us
and then yeah it'll be very easy to
vosalize us. So that will be the
situation if we don't take space
seriously.
Pascar Bandit says a certain curlyhaired
man claims to be ex CIA on various
podcasts tries to dissect how
intelligence works, what things CIA has
done etc. It feels like this is a plot
or disinformation campaign just as UFOs
are seen only in the US. You see in
intelligence you also have counter
intelligence.
When it comes to propaganda you have
information you also have
disinformation.
If you want to remain obscure you not
you can have people who pose as your
agents or ex- agents and they go and
spread misinformation about you.
So this is an old tried andrue tactic. I
mean if somebody is really ex CIA, you
think that person will be they will
tolerate that person going and spilling
all the secrets on YouTube. No way they
will tolerate that. So if somebody's
going around doing that, it means that
they have the blessings to go and spread
misinformation about the CIA or
whatever.
Yeah. So I would agree with you. It's
very it makes a lot of sense to be very
skeptical about such people who claim to
be X Y X this X that and I know
everything and let me tell you all the
secrets. It doesn't work like that.
Nobody will be tolerated. Nobody will be
allowed to tell secrets if those are
real secrets that are being dulged.
Something will be done about such about
such individuals. But clearly nothing is
being done about him which means that he
has their blessings to spread
misinformation.
Uh our friend again with very naughty
name is saying your opinion on Munir
becoming the first chief of defense
forces of Pakistan.
Uh should we ensure that he remains not
only first but the last CDF of the
temporary nation? I would say yes.
What's my opinion? I have no opinion.
He's become the first CDF. It means he's
pretty powerful in the Pakistani
military. He's all powerful. He has
given himself all kinds of titles, field
marshal and whatnot. Good for him.
Should we ensure that he remains the
last CD of the temporary nation?
Ideally, we should. Ideally, we should.
Yes. But will we do that? Time will
tell. I ideally we should ensure he's
the last CDF.
Kiran Mori says Indian Navy have some
upcoming projects for submarine like 76
I767.
I have also heard these these various
names. Project 75 something etc.
Good that we have it but we would like
to see the outcome. India should have I
would dozens of submarines.
We have a very large area of interest,
geographical area of interest, maritime
area of interest. We have this wonderful
set of slogans, right? The Indian Ocean
is our strategic backyard. Blah blah
blah. You think it becomes a strategic
backyard because you are you keep on
repeating that you have to make it your
strategic backyard by taking ownership.
How do you take ownership? By having a
constant visible presence.
How do you maintain a constant vis
visible presence? By having constant
patrolling of this gigantic piece of
maritime real estate with your warships
and submarines. Wherever somebody comes,
they should see into the Indian Navy
everywhere. That's how it becomes your
strategic backyard. Not by saying talk
talk talk talk talk talk talk talk talk
talk talk talk talk talk talk talk talk.
So if we have this projects and all good
let something happen as a consequence.
We should have at least 50 submarines if
we have a strategic backyard that large.
Ideally we should have 100 submarines.
Right now we have less than 20 which is
which is a joke which is sad which is
tragic. So we have this submarine
projects that have been going on for
decades. I've been hearing
needs to speed up. We need to see
results.
Okay. Gajapati Dev says, "Any update on
next book parts? Waiting for it. I am
wondering whether I should release the
remaining parts online or whether I
should simply finish it and put it out
in the physical shape. Maybe I should do
that." Yeah. So, I'm obviously working
on this stuff. It's not like I've
stopped working because I stopped live
streaming that stuff. Yeah. I'm working
on it. Um I'm expecting that the first
full complete book will be will be
completed in the first quarter of the
next year. In the next year I'm planning
three at least
three ideally. So let's see maybe I
should stop releasing these book
sections by section by section by
section and just put the whole thing out
in the physical shape. If you can have a
little bit of patience I'll do that.
Okay, Rahul Kumar says oh okay this
question we already took but okay should
India resume nuclear testing the US have
announced that they will do so Pakistan
they say is currently doing it please to
read last question
I don't know what to read last question
means but okay should India resume
nuclear testing see Trump has claimed
that Pakistan is testing nuclear weapons
and that's what that's the justification
he's using uh to say that he wants to
resume American nuclear testing So what
should India do? India should not go and
start testing right right away. Let's
wait for somebody to test first. Let the
Americans test. If the Americans test,
the Japanese the sorry not the Japanese.
If the Americans test, the Russians will
go ahead and test and the Chinese will
also likely test. Then we should go
ahead and test. So at least two other
nations should test after which we
should we should test. We should not
just unilaterally start testing
otherwise they will impose sanction
sanctions on us.
Um, BL why did I say that?
Did you search about Eva Flinger brick?
It's some Dutch lady I think on very
very active on Twitter. I did not look
into in great detail about her but yeah
it's some a lady whose portrait is a
right-winger and she's Dutch I think and
uh she is conservative of some kind or
something. That's what I can tell you.
Okay, Sam the Gamer says, "Why didn't
India use Vietnam and Taiwan alternative
trade options? They offer products we
need at similar rates. Why do we depend
on China?" Huge admirer. Thank you very
much for that. Um,
why do we depend on China?
We should obviously have diversified our
procurement sources for everything.
But maybe it's like China produces
things that Vietnam and Taiwan don't
produce. See, Taiwan, what does it
produce? It produces semiconductors. It
produces chips. It has TSMC and a couple
of other companies that are the bulk of
the uh producers of of chips and
semiconductor
products. So they don't produce other
things, right? That the Chinese produce.
When it comes to Vietnam,
once again, they will not have the kind
of production capability capability that
the Chinese have. The Vietnamese don't
export rare earths, neither do the
Taiwanese. So there are lots of things
that only China does.
Right? And that's why we are depending
on that. So my my point is instead of
depending on Vietnam and Taiwan and
instead of just depending on China, we
should set up all these production lines
in our own country so that we can
manufacture everything we need instead
of being dependent on a nation like
China which is hostile to us. That's
what we should do. That's the ideal
situation. And we have this make in
India slogan that's been around for 11
12 years. But what's come out of it thus
far? Anything major? Not really. Which
is which is rather
you know which is unfortunate.
Arad dwari says sufficient macros gym
hypertrophy and OMAD vegan.
So you into gym you are going after
hypertrophy which means you are lifting
weights. You are doing vegan OMAD. One
meal a day vegan. sufficient macros. Uh
vegan means no vegetarian which vegan
and vegetarian different which means you
are not consuming any dairy products. So
where are you getting your protein from?
See vegan diet will definitely give you
sufficient carbs. Yeah. If you have
beans and stuff and if you eat beans and
lentils you will also get protein.
Uh it will give you way too much carbs
along with the protein. So in that case
the macros could be sufficient but
you'll have to burn off the excess
calories by being physically more
active. So if you want to get get let's
say 150 grams of protein through vegan
means through lentils and um beans etc.
I think your calorie intake will be
3,500 or something per day maybe 4,000.
So you need to be sufficiently active to
burn that off per day. In that case, you
will not only have sufficient micro
macros and protein for hypertrophy, but
you will also be in good shape. Yeah,
that's what I would say off the top of
my head without looking into the
specific macros, but yeah, it should
work that way. All the best, sir. Do
well, bulk up.
Uh can have an understanding Russia
series maybe in the future. Look, I am
not even able to work on the
understanding America right now. You
want understanding Russia?
I I look there's a lot I need to do.
There's a lot. The past four years I've
been speaking. It's time I start
publishing books. So that's going to be
the focus this coming year. That's what
I'm focusing on right now.
So that's the deal. Eventually I'll take
up these u suggestions and hopefully
whatever is possible I'll do. But thank
you for the suggestion sir. Uh Anoj says
please guide where to start new
please guide where to start new channel
real Indian history. Well whatever you
are if you are starting a new YouTube
channel about Indian history I would
recommend you start with whatever your
expertise is. So if you're an expert on
let's say the history of Odisha you
start with that. Make 10 20 videos as
many as as possible based on the
subjects you know the best then you can
branch out from there. Maybe your
expertise is Punjab history. Maybe your
expertise is Tamil history. Maybe your
expertise is is is is
Maharashtra history. Whatever it is
whatever you know best start with that.
That's what I would say and then you can
go beyond that eventually once those
things are taken care of. That's what I
would say. All the best, sir.
UMX says, "I was pressured by family
into a Jesuit college. It's a waste.
BCOM that doesn't fit my goals. Also has
6 6 a.m. timing."
What on earth? 6 a.m. timing. Indian
colleges are so horrible. Why? I have
never heard of an Indian college that
has a 6 a.m. timing. My goodness. It's a
Jesuit college, so it must be okay.
Whatever.
Uh so what's the question? Why are
Indian colleges terrible? The Indian
education system is terrible. So
obviously everything else everything
that's associated with it is going to be
terrible. That's the problem. Anyway, it
is what it is.
Do the best that you can with it. Just
get your thing done. Get your degree and
get out. That's all. All the best. Uh
VSVS says DRDO and Safhan will develop
will develop most advanced French fifth
generation jet engine and will get full
transfer of technology with all
technology including single crystal
blades and property rights deal
finalized on 24th November. Question by
Adwit. It's not a question it's a
statement. What's the question?
Yes. So DRD and Safh have uh
uh announced this deal. uh India will
develop a fifth generation jet engine.
It's not not going to be a French jet
engine. It's going to be an indoor
French jet engine but the
intellectual rights will be with India.
The full technology will be Indian
single crystal blades etc. So I suppose
we must have paid them a lot of money
for that and uh yeah I think it's great.
Like I've been saying for a long time we
need to acquire this technology no
matter what happens. Buy, beg, borrow,
steal, whatever. So we are buying it.
Good job. Finally get it done as soon as
possible. Test it out rigorously and
then start flying with the engines.
Animeh Paul says, "In a day and age of
extreme commoditization and over
consumerism, how can we as a society
stay focused on meaningful goals instead
of getting pulled into the toxic pursuit
of status and showmanship?" You know,
the nation needs to have a mission.
Does our nation have a mission?
The Chinese nation has a mission. The
great rejuvenation of China by 2049 or
whatever it is. They have a clear
mission. Their leader has given them a
mission. Everyone knows what direction
they are supposed to go in.
Everyone knows what their role in it is.
What is India's mission?
Do our leaders have a mission? Have they
given all citizens a clarion call of
what we are going to do? what which
direction we have to be in and what our
target is by 2050 or whatever. If you
have that end state in mind, then you
know exactly what your role in it is.
But we don't have a national mission of
any kind for some reason.
So that's why everybody is going in
whatever direction. Everybody is
self-interested, self uh self-centered
and so on. We need leadership. We need
better leadership.
So how can we as a society stay focused
on meaningful goals? Let's say you don't
have good leaders. Nobody has given you
a goal. You have to find a goal for
yourself.
Something that means something for you.
Something that makes you want to wake up
early in the morning and get going.
Whatever it is for you, something
personal, right? And hopefully if
everybody is engaged in something, you
know, something passionately like this,
then maybe the country goes in the right
direction. That's what we need to do
individually.
Sangam Kumar says is Russia versus NATO
inevitable as Germans analyze not
necessarily
it will be a disaster if Russia and NATO
go to war.
It will lead possibly to a nuclear
exchange which will be the end of the
world. So I don't think Russia versus
NATO is inevitable. Who controls NATO?
The US controls NATO. The US will use
NATO to try and you know destabilize
Russia. maybe maybe maybe
contain Russia,
maybe degrade Russia's capabilities,
economy, etc. That can't risk a direct
confrontation
because that draws the US into it. The
US versus Russia, face to face, fighting
punch to punch. That can go wrong very
rapidly. So that's the last thing the US
wants, a direct confrontation. So I
don't think it's inevitable. I hope it
never happens. The Germans, the Germans
are being used the way the Americans are
using the Japanese just to ratchet up
the tensions and to issue threats and
warnings. But Germany is simply a sock
puppet for the US just like Japan is
unfortunately.
>> Okay, once again I will not say that
name. [laughter]
Many people justify colonialism by
giving example of Sudan saying locals
slaughtering each other would be better
if it was still under British control.
What's my opinion? My opinion is you
know what every nation every part of the
world has its own culture
who is to decide which culture is better
who which is worse who decides do the
westerners decide and they pass judgment
on which culture is good which culture
is bad who are they to decide what gives
them the right to decide which culture
is superior maybe Sudhan has people
slaughtering each other maybe let's say
it is their culture let them exercise
their right to their culture Why do you
have to interfere? Why don't you mind
your own goddamn business and stay where
you are? H who gives you the right to
determine which culture is good, which
is bad and what should happen, what
people should do, what they should not
do. Who the hell are you people who
decide that? So this is not a
justification.
This is a very imperialistic world way
of view of the world.
So we need to reject that and let people
try to justify it. Do we have to agree
with it? We don't have to agree with it.
And maybe they're giving the example of
Sudan. What about other countries?
Did the native aboriginal Australians
slaughter each other? They were living
in peace. But they had this huge
valuable continent that the that the
whites wanted. So they classified the
locals as flora and fauna as animals
essentially and took over the whole
place. What justifies that? There is no
justification for brutality, barbarism,
colonialism, all that. Nothing can
justify that.
VSBS says NATO war company Kapad Lloyd
are now operating in our eastern front
Bangladesh ports. They've tightened the
screws in Suez Canal during Hamash
Israel clash. Thoughts questioned by
Chatanya? Well, Chatanya
there's nothing surprising about this.
See Bangladesh
has undergone this coup. Shakina was
ousted and now the army is ruling
Bangladesh and they have this puppet
Muhammad Yunus who is the alleged leader
of Bangladesh but he's just a puppet and
Bangladesh is now a vasal of the US. So
in 1971
we broke Bangladesh free of US control
by liberating Bangladesh from Pakistan
because Pakistan was a US vasal at the
time. It's it it is again one now. So 71
we transformed East Pakistan into
Bangladesh. Now because of the coup in
Bangladesh, Bangladesh is now once again
de facto East Pakistan and they're
allowing American companies etc to you
know to set up shop over there. So no
surprise there. So we're going to have
to be now careful about what's happening
in Bangladesh because before Shik
Hassina came to power we had that
Khalidazi or whatever her name was. She
was in power. was very strongly
anti-India and she was harboring all
kinds of separatists and terrorists in
her territory who would then cause all
kinds of havoc in our far east etc. So
we're going to have to be very careful
about this. Yeah. And uh cruising the
Suez Canal during um look when it comes
to Egypt etc. you're going to have a
sizable significant US and Western
presence there. So no surprise that they
are doing whatever they're doing there.
Okay.
Um,
why do many Jews promote the idea of
Western civilization?
I don't know. I suppose the Jews, most
Jews now see them as part of the
western, see themselves as part of the
Western world. See, Israel is a nation
in West Asia, right? But when it comes
to sporting activities, Israel
participates in European championships.
So, Israel does not see itself as an
Asian Asian nation. It sees itself as a
Western nation. So maybe the Jewish
people today see themselves as part of
the Western world, which would kind of
explain why they promote the idea of
Western civilization perhaps. I'm just
speculating. I don't know, but maybe
that's the case.
Godliness says, "Will you ever
participate in politics? Change will
only come if we become lawmakers. We
need to get into the system." I don't
know how to play politics. It's it's a
very dirty world and u I have never
considered it. Maybe I will most likely
never participate in politics. Uh maybe
some of you will I'm hoping that the
viewers of this show some of you will be
the future leaders of this country.
That's what I'm hoping.
Maybe I hope so. I hope that some of you
some of you who are watching right now
will go on to lead the country and take
it in a in a much better direction.
That's what I hope. We need young people
to go ahead with this. Look at me. Am I
that young now?
>> All right.
Uh
Ra
I'm sorry I can't pronounce it. Rahun
Raj says people think robots in army is
bipedal robots like terminator but
drones are robots without any limitation
of limbs and Z-axis right drones are
robots drones are autonomous or
semi-autonomous killer robots they can
kill humans they can take out vehicles
they can take out tanks they can even
take out other things
we have this imagination that robots are
bipedal humanoid structures or or or or
things machines
like the Terminator thing with a with a
face and red eyes and stuff. That's not
necessarily it. You can have robot dogs
that carry weapons and have
unairring aim. You can have snake like
robots. You can have all kinds of robots
in all kinds of different shapes and
sizes. Even those bipedal robots that
you watch dancing around, they can
scuttle around like a crab on all fours.
Yeah. So, yeah, there's no limitation.
There's no limitation of limbs or
whatever. Robots can come on all kinds
of different sizes, shapes, whatever.
Your drones are robots, aren't they?
Killer robots.
Okay. Um, Gagan Bi Agni Purush says,
"Namaskar. What happened to USA series
of yours?" I, it is right now on ice.
Uh, I'm focusing on something else right
now. I'm focusing on writing, which is
very important. I will restart it,
resume it at the right time. Right now,
it is on hold.
Um, [clears throat]
first snail says, "Believe in cosmic ray
theory that hit aircraft." Did a theory
hit aircraft
or did cosmic rays hit aircraft? Cosmic
rays hit aircraft all the time. Do you
know why your cell phone loses charge?
You charge your cell phone 100%. Keep it
overnight, it's no longer 100%. You
don't charge it for 3 days, it's going
to go down to like 20% or whatever your
phone does. Why does the charge go down?
Even if you don't light up the screen,
why does the charge go down? Because of
cosmic rays towards one of the factors
is cosmic rays.
Yeah.
So cosmic rays hit everything. The
earth's magnetic field, the van Allen
belts etc. They shield us to a large
extent from the most harmful cosmic
rays. But cosmic rays do get through and
they do hit us.
So it's a known fact that cosmic rays do
penetrate the atmosphere and hit the
surface. They do and they would
certainly hit aircraft. So I'm not sure
about any other theory. This is what I
know. Okay. Vsvs says a question by Eric
Twin.
How to get a girlfriend? How to get a
girlfriend? First of all, speak to
girls.
There's nothing wrong in getting a
girlfriend. It's what everybody, it's a
natural part of life. How do you get a
girlfriend? You start by speaking to
girls. And don't try to impress girls by
by being trying to be something you
somebody you're not.
Don't ever try to impress anybody. Just
be yourself. Be the authentic person
that you are. Don't try to pretend to be
something else. Don't try to be super
impressive. Just be who you are.
If you want to impress others, try to
improve yourself over time. But the
point is, you can't get a girlfriend if
you're super shy, if you're scared, if
you don't talk to girls. Just talk to
girls, be yourself, make friends, and
then maybe one of those friends will
could become a girlfriend of yours.
Yeah, that's as simple as it gets.
That's all.
Pu
Pu IQ says, "What's the connection
between Jews and Yavas?" Zero, no
connection. That's the answer. That's
the only answer I can give you. No
connection whatsoever.
Aditi says, "Recently, Argentinian Navy
found a huge swarm of Chinese fishing
ships in their waters. Could you explain
what's actually going on there? Can I
use can a country use fishing ships to
access foreign waters? They're not
supposed to. See, every nation has
something called an exclusive economic
zone in which only they can exploit the
resources of the waters. So there is
something called territorial waters and
then there is something called an EEZ
exclusive economic zone. U let's let's
quickly take a look at this what it
looks like. Okay.
Uh territorial
waters
versus EZ.
So territorial waters are up to 12
nautical miles but EEZ is a further area
up to 200 nautical miles from the
baseline. Okay, that's about it. So this
so so this Chinese vessels they are in
international waters but they are within
the exclusive intern economic zone of
Argentina and they are doing fishing and
trolling there. They are breaking
international law and the Chinese have
depleted the oceans in their region in
the south south China sea etc etc and
now they're going they're sending
hundreds of fishing ships all the way to
the coastline of Argentina and they are
sucking out all the fish and the marine
life there. This is predatory behavior.
The Chinese are parasites. This is
parasitic behavior. Seriously. So what
the Chinese are doing is absolutely
illegal.
Illegal, unethical, immoral, predatory,
parasitical, whatever you want to say.
That's why you can't trust this nation.
You simply can't trust. They want to
turn everybody into beggars.
Absolutely barbaric behavior by China.
This is this is outright theft of of
marine resources.
Shocking.
Dimewma says, "Is there any way to bring
back the Saraspati
the river?" You mean
how do you bring her back? You would
have to change the climate for the river
to come back. Yeah, sure. You could try
and engineer the course of the river.
But see, what was the river fed by? It
was fed by two two things. One was
glacial melt water from the Himalayas,
the melting of snows and ice in the
Himalayas. And secondly, more
importantly, the rainy season, the
monsoon rains. So 6 8,000 years ago, the
monsoon in India was way heavier than it
is today. And it was what mainly
sustained this gigantic great river, the
Saraspati. Then the monsoon declined
over the past 8,000 years from 6,000 BC
until today. And eventually it was it
came down to such an extent that the
Saraspati dried out in the southern half
of her course. So how do you bring this
great river back? You have to engineer a
heavier monsoon every year. How do you
do that? You don't know how to do it.
So, and the question is why do you want
to bring the river back?
Maybe we did something that caused her
to leave us. So, maybe that is something
we need to change in ourselves. Yeah. Uh
MK says will what will be the
consequences if chooses to come out of
the EU and NATO? It will be ostracized.
The Americans will punish it
tremendously. They will isolate the
nation. They will try to destroy its
economy. Very simple.
How dare a nation try to escape
slavery? Essentially,
escape vasal status. How dare somebody
do that? No one does that. You do that,
you're going to be destroyed. The
consequences will be severe if France
tries to do that. In in the past, France
did come out of the primary membership
of NATO, etc., but it stayed a part of
the EU.
Uh but France is the only nation that
can think of doing such things but it
the consequences will be severe if it
does that. Okay. Balky today says
Clinton India visit terror attack in
Jammu Kashmir. JD
visit Palam attack. Who's JD? JD Vance.
Okay. Clinton
JD Vance visited Palum attack. Putin
visit indigo fiasco. Does deep state
sabotage or military government at will?
Look, India is
allegedly penetrated to some levels. At
some levels, the deep state
has assets
at various levels in India. No question
about it. Some are open assets, some are
covert assets.
I'm not naming anybody by the way. Okay?
So yeah, I'm not naming anybody at all.
But yes, India is penetrated like so
many countries are.
The Chinese were also penetrated, but
they did something about it in the
2010s.
They did they they they cleaned up
things in China. In our case, uh we are
way more penetrated.
So yeah um I don't know about our
military
but um
yeah India can be affected by things uh
that uh that the deep state engineers
for sure indeed.
Okay. VSVs says, "Floxy nosy
nihilificated
and defenistrated the Bangalian tea out
of James. [laughter]
Fuxy flocksification."
Floxy nosi nihilification, right? Nihil
pilicated in defenistrated the
panglosian tea out of James. You know
what? Actually, James, I appreciate
James. He gives me the opportunity to
speak about issues that sometimes I
don't get to speak about. So I I
appreciate James. I really do. And yeah,
so thank you James once again. Thank
you. Now uh hyphen says I have been
noticing the increase in Pakistani
people in the UK for the past few years.
Okay, you are very accurate. There's
majority Pakistan in Pakistanis in few
towns already. You know
I visited London first time in the year
2002. I saw Pakistanis all over the
place. I mean I saw people who look like
us.
And you could tell that some of them are
not exactly as they're Pakistanis,
right? Uh because you can't really tell
from our features, but certain things
give it away. So there's there were
Pakistanis all over the place in 2002
itself.
Every shop you go to, every road you
street you walk on, Pakistanis. I mean,
yeah, Pakistanis today, I suppose there
are lots of Bangladeshes as well. So the
UK is very fond of Pakistan.
I mean Rotherham, the Pakistanis were
given a free hand. Do whatever you want
with our girls, right?
I don't know what kind of nation the UK
is. It's a nation of cowards and losers.
Their authorities are a bunch of
cowards. Their people are a bunch of
cowards. They are passionate when it
comes to cricket and football.
But when when it comes to defending your
women folk,
nothing sheep. So what can I say? It's
it's
some part of me feels sorry for the UK.
Yeah. For the people of the UK. Some
part of me at some level I feel sorry
for them.
Uh Critical Return says quantum
Darwinism versus many words theory. Who
wins? Um,
ask me about Copenhagen versus Gar
versus Benny Worlds. Manny Worlds
I don't know who wins. It's it's
um
we don't have the answer yet. There are
various physicists, you know, some
physicists are on this side, some
physicists are on that side. There are
many physicists who are in favor of the
many worlds interpretation.
Many physicists who will say that the
Copenhagen interpretation makes way more
sense. Where am I? I would like the many
words interpretation to be true.
Actually, it'll be fun. I don't know who
wins. It's too early to say. We don't
have the answer yet. Okay. Vssvs says,
"Question by another." Pegasus 3642.
Does Indian point of view of
Indo-Uropean history does it have any
chance of being the norm? India becomes
more dominant sooner or later. Look, the
truth should initi should eventually
win.
The truth has to win eventually.
the Indian POV. I don't care whose POV
it is. If David Reich turns out to be
true, I will accept his POV is the
correct thing. But I have studied this.
I have examined this in great detail.
This entire Arian invasion or migration
thing is is a lie.
It's a lie. I have I've gone through
different phases of analyzing this. For
the longest time of in my life, I
believed in the arin invasion theory. I
believed that I was the descendant of
white-kinned people who came from Europe
and uh conquered India. I believe
believed that I believed my at least
some of my ancestors were white people
who came from Central Asia or Europe or
whatever. That's what I believed then
and and I was active on social media and
I had these people who kept on telling
me that please look into the invention
theory. It's all a lie. I used to get
annoyed with it. I used to get annoyed
with them. I I used to say, "How does it
matter what happened 5,000 years ago? If
the facts are the facts and accept them,
right? Why do you have to be all like
why do you have to go against everything
that comes out of the west?" Then one
day I said, "Let me just look into this.
I mean, I have believed this theory my
entire life, but let me look at the
actual research papers, the actual data,
not at what textbooks are telling me or
authors are telling me. Let me actually
look at the data points themselves." And
I spent a few months going through the
various genetic papers, archaeological
research, the actual research papers,
not opinions.
And I was astonished. I was shocked. I
was flabbergasted.
See, I have a background in theoretical
physics and mathematics. It gives me a
gigantic advantage. I can understand
genetics research papers. I can
understand research papers in other
sciences.
and also sociology and whatn not easy to
understand.
I may not be able to do the research but
but I can understand what the research
papers are telling me are are are trying
to convey and I saw that this is all a
lie
and I in in which year I I put out I I I
wrote this paper right u Arian invasion
myth
uh India facts
so I wrote this article it was published
in Indiafacts.org OG RN invision myth it
was published in 2017 in this paper in
this in this article I essentially
you know completed the jigsaw puzzle I
put out all the evidence that's from
various different domains genetics and
archaeology and myth even mythology
literature literary evidence
all these different things I put them
together and I showed that you know what
this entire thing is a god damn myth.
It's a lie. I was shocked. It took me a
while to understand what I had
discovered.
So truth, the truth will come out
eventually.
Right now they're still trying to push
this this they have turned the migration
the the invasion into a migration. Then
they will say it's a tourism. Then
they'll say it's a picnic. They'll keep
on trying to do this. But in 20 30 years
eventually there'll be no there'll be no
more lies to tell. So it's going to
happen. And obviously as India becomes
more dominant it will happen.
Uh Shivatsa says does a black hole fully
evaporate or does or do quantum gravity
limits hold the process at the plank
scale leaving behind a stable plank
scale remnant? That's a very good
question you ask. That's a very good
question. Do we have the answer?
We're not sure. Is there a plank scale
remnant? Is there a plankon or a
cornucopion?
Have you heard that term before? Let's
see. I haven't heard heard that for a
while. Kucopians,
no, no, no,
not that.
Uh, cornucopians are theoretical and
finally wrong.
Okay. What about plank scale remnants?
Plank scale remnants.
Yeah. PBH. Yeah. Hypothetical stable
plank mass objects left behind from
extin etc. So yeah, this is indeed a
very viable uh outcome.
See the smallest scale we can that is
allowed in theoretical physics based on
what we know based on everything we
understand about quantum mechanics. The
smallest allowed length scale is the
plank scale. The one plank length which
is of the order of 10 to - 35 m. So can
a black hole evaporate below that scale?
It should not be able to. Yeah. So the
process should or or could possibly halt
at the plank scale and black hole
evaporation should not be possible
beyond that which would indicate which
would mean that the universe would be
filled with this plank scale remnants
that are no longer black holes which are
stable particles pure mass which would
which would have very interesting
consequences for cold dark matter. So
yeah
VSVS says interesting okay what's your f
who is your favorite guitarist look like
if you ask me what's my favorite food my
favorite movie I won't have one answer I
can give you five five examples my top
five my top favorite five guitarists
who would that be uh Jimmy Page
Jimmyi Hendris oh two jimmies we have
there Jimmy Page Jimmyi Hendris who else
who
I'm sure there's more. Why am I not able
to think of anyone [laughter] right now?
Uh
uh David Gilmore. Okay, I'll give you
three. Jimmy Page, Jimmy Hendricks,
David Gilmore. I'm sure there's more. I
can give you 10 more, but yeah, let's
stop at three. Okay. Okay. We still we
have crossed three hours 20 minutes. I
still have 20 questions to take. How
privileged am I? Uh Rajat says best
definition of consciousness I found as
per adit vanta even what's the
definition
even shinger after reading vanta said
the plurality that you perceive is only
in appearance and used to say atma is
brahman what is the definition
you have found the best definition of
consciousness per adita vanta what is
the definition
what is it I don't want to know what
shinger said after reading I just tell
me the definition because I seek it
I seek the definition of consciousness.
I've never found one. I seek a
scientific definition of consciousness.
If you have the definition, if you found
the definition, why don't you put it
here? I don't care what X person or Y
person said. I that doesn't impress me.
I only care about the objective fact. I
don't care what Schroinger or Einstein
or God said about it.
The plurality that we perceive is only
an appearance. And I don't care what
somebody said. Just give me the
definition. I seek it myself. If you
have it, why why are you withholding it?
I seek the definition. I don't I've
never found a definition. I have never
found a precise scientific definition of
consciousness. If you have it, please
share it. I don't care what somebody
said about it. Doesn't impress me.
Please tell us about Bulakkeshi and Vat
Pichal. I don't know about them. Sorry.
Dirj
[laughter]
Kamat says will distribute nukes create
a multipolar world. Oh, it sure will.
It'll be fun. Yeah. Everybody take a
few.
[laughter]
That'll be fun. Imagine every African
dictator gets 10 nukes.
[laughter]
It will certainly create a multipolar
world. It will.
But it will be a chaotic world. Okay.
VSVS says requests mod to review Ankush
Roy.
Let me see who is this Ankush Roy and
what is this person up to?
Ankush Roy.
Ankush Roy. Ankush Roy. What's going on?
Are you being naughty, sir? Ankush Roy.
Uh
maybe this will have to be looked into
in the future later at a later point.
I just uh let me just finish this now. I
still have like 15 questions to go. Uh
Moji Pio Africanos Moji Pio Africanos
says, "Do you think the buildup by the
Chinese on our borders could lead to an
actual conflict by 2030 or do we act on
sin the PK before that leads to it?" No.
book say the BK if we do something the
Chinese will take action over here.
Why are the Chinese building up a
military presence on our borders?
Because they would like the option to do
something. It will be it will cost the
Chinese less to start a war with India
than to start a war with Taiwan.
And if Xiinping is under political
pressure or whatever, he would like a
military victory somewhere. And if he
believes that he can inflict a defeat on
India, then he will take action.
So this Chinese this build up by the
Chinese on our borders could it lead to
an actual conflict by 2013? Maybe it
could lead to a conflict by 2026 or 27.
We have to be very careful about that.
Okay. We'll have to be very careful
about that. Vbsayush Singh requests
comment on China locking Japanese plane.
I'm not aware of it. The Chinese have
locked Japanese plane. What? They took a
key and locked it
or did they jam some electronics on the
plane? What exactly happened? Uh let me
see. Let me see the news. Uh China locks
China locks
Japanese plane
planet. Really? [laughter]
Japanese plane. China Japan flights
fight explodes midair.
A Chinese jet pointed a radar at a
Japanese aircraft.
Okay, there's nothing to comment about
in this. This is just a routine nasty
occurrence by the Chinese. They do that
all the time to everybody. Taiwanese,
Japanese, whatever. Yeah, VSB says,
"When will understanding America
restart?" Not at any not in the short to
medium term. Maybe in the longer term. I
I I right now have other projects that I
that are at a higher priority right now.
So not immediately, not soon, but
eventually it will because it's a very
worthwhile and valuable project, but not
right now. Uh Riser says, "Open map go
to Andra search church random area." I'm
aware. I'm aware. I'm aware
all over the place. Everywhere.
Let's do it. Let's do it. Since you are
saying
let's do it.
India is is sleeping. I don't know what
the Indian government is doing like what
why are we building all this
infrastructure? Why are we building the
economy to give it away to to outsiders?
So this is Andhra Pradesh.
Let's go to any random area and let's
see church.
Zoom in.
Now once again church
all over the place.
This is
industrial scale demographic
re-engineering that's happening in
India. This is a threat to India
civilization.
I am not against any any religion but
this is being done on an industrial
scale by pouring in hundreds of billions
of dollars every year. This is what I
have an issue with
and the Indian government is sleeping on
this absolutely sleeping not concerned
which is what can I say it's it's so
incredibly disappointing
so yeah that's the situation right now
looks like we are simply building our
economy
you know building up our economy
building up our infrastructure building
everything to hand it over to the
descendants of the Bangladesh Rohingyas
and whoever is else has been converted
that's what what we doing right now vss
says, "Question by Sam the Gamer. Is
China failing to see how its unresolved
issues with Russia and India empower the
US? Why isn't it clearing the path for
RAIC?"
But China is very aware of what's
happening. China is a very wise,
practical, pragmatic nation. They
genuinely believe that they can take on
the US on their own and vasalize Russia
and fragment India.
And maybe they have a game plan for
that. The Chinese are wise. Maybe you
are failing to see the things that they
are able to see.
Okay. The Chinese are going to up the
anti- visavi Russia also in the next 2
three years. They will start making
territorial claims on Russia. They're
going to start playing nasty with Russia
also by latest by 2030.
Why would the Chinese want RAC when it
can can be se only? They genuinely
believe their their time has come.
That's why they're doing this.
Okay. VSBS once again says, "Do you
think India can build expensive
colliders even with freebies,
but the issue is approvals, corruption,
and specific department funding cuts or
no vision?"
See, we can still build expensive
colliders.
The question is who's going to operate
the colliders? Do we have the right? Do
we first of all
have the vision to make India a leading
scientific power? Do we have the vision?
The vision has to come from the top.
Do we have the vision is the first
question. Approvals. Oh my god. The
bureaucracy, the red tape. I mean
the prime minister approved
the construction of an Indian version of
LIGO in 2015.
2015.
Let me show you.
Okay, let's go to the Wikipedia page for
LIGO India.
LIIGO is the instrument that detected
gravit gravitational wave for the first
time. LIGO India Indian initiative in
gravitational wave blah blah blah. So
purpose funding etc. 20 2015 where is
2015? This was announced in 2015.
2015.
So essentially the prime minister
gave the approval for LIGO in principle
in 2015. Then MOU was signed in 2016.
Okay. So what has happened?
2015 is a decade ago, right? What
happened? Where is legal India?
location let's say the location
district of Maharashtra etc etc etc now
let us see on the map what is the status
okay let's see on the map since we're
doing this
so where is India
India where it's here let us see has
something been been constructed
do you see anything
that has been constructed here. I can
see a small little thing here.
Yeah, this is the facility.
It's a corporate office that they have
built. Where is the instrument? The
approval was given 10 years ago. There
is absolutely no vision in India.
Okay, that's the problem. So with
without a vision, what's the what what
collider will will will India build?
Nothing. There's no scientific vision.
There's no ambition, there's nothing.
Positive coffee.
Thank you very much, sir. Thank you.
A Rahul says, "Hinduism has never been
about following a specific book." Yes
sir, I know that. Why are people
nowadays trying to frame it as a
religion of a book which they like?
Because Indians have lost touch with
their culture. Indians are dasinated.
Indians want everything to be like the
West today. And there are various new
fangled aspects of Hinduism or or or new
fangled cults that claim to be Hindu
cults that have emerged in in the past
few decades. Some of whom portray the
gods they don't like as demiggods
and so much more. So there is all this
little infighting, all this little
competition etc. Everyone's trying to
say this is the book I like. you know my
the the the founder of my cult wrote
this book which is an edited version of
the older book and you have to read this
only and that sort of thing. I am not
naming anybody specifically. I'm just
saying overall this is the situation.
So Indians are increasingly more and
more dassinated.
They are losing touch with their
heritage with their culture. So they are
seeing everything through a western
through western lenses and that's why
this this situation exists.
Sundesh says is there any sabotage
behind the indigo crisis which why did
it happen during Putin's visit? There
are many experienced people in Indigo
and did not predict it. I don't know if
there is sabotage or not. I am not an
insider. I don't know what happened. All
I can say is the government of India
needs to take the strictest action
against the people responsible within
Indigo. This is unacceptable.
There have to be consequences for this.
This caused a tremendous amount of
damage to tens of thousands of people,
to India's economy, to India's
reputation and god knows what else. The
government of India has to to hold
Indigo and the and the relevant people
accountable and take the strictest
possible action. That's what needs to
happen.
Positive coffee says big fan. Thank you,
sir. Why are Indians nowadays B12 and
vitamin D deficient? What how does your
diet look like and what's your source of
protein?
Why are Indians B12 and vitamin D
deficient? Vitamin D comes from sunlight
does it
all you have to do is spend 15 minutes
in the sunlight sunlight. But most
Indians especially in cities etc they
never go out in the sun.
So that's why the vitamin D deficiency
is there. Vitamin D is is it sunlight?
Vitamin D is from sunlight, sun
exposure. Yeah. Uh B12, I'm not really
sure. I suppose they don't eat balanced
diet and all that. What does my diet
look like? What's my source of protein?
Well, let's not go into those matters.
My diet is a balanced diet. I get
sufficient protein, at least 150 grams a
day. My diet isn't always very
disciplined. That's which is why I'm
slightly not very fit right now. I need
to
get back into shape soon.
VSVS says, "Do you think INR around 90
is good?" I don't look I am not an
economist. Economics is one thing that's
not my forte. So I don't know. Um I
suppose if if that's a lower exchange
rate or higher exchange rate for visa
with the Indian rupee then it could be
beneficial if we are exporting but we
are not a major exporting country. We
are importing more than we export.
Right? That's the problem.
Um
so yeah look this these economic topics
that's that's something I can answer not
right away I would have to look into it.
Yeah. So yeah I can't answer this
question right now. Sorry. Spade 2 says
we would love to contribute and assist
you in any shape or form as we want to
learn more from you for example mods 4
channel etc. Thank you. Um, thank you
very much for the suggestion and the
offer and I will uh consider that
seriously. Thank you. UMX Glowhaha says
uh thoughts on self help books. I've
when I was in my 20s and even early 30s
I read a whole bunch of self-help books.
Did they help me? Not really. Not
really.
It may help you. It depends. It depends.
Um my personal experience has been is
that you know it's overall eventually I
I have come to think of these self-help
books as a waste of time. They go on
forever and you to really search for the
two three pieces of information that are
relevant which you could write in like
you know like five pages essentially but
they turn that into a 300page book and
so on. So most of the self-help books
are just fluff just unhelpful.
There may be a few that I'm not aware of
but whatever.
Di Shukla says how can I be a successful
also financially polymath journalist
like you? I'm in interested in multiple
areas. You have to spend all your time
reading and studying these things and
you have to be able to
to monetize some of these some of this
knowledge and skills that's what you to
do right. So if you want to be a
polymath or a general generalist
I'm not sure I'm a generalist. I am a
specialist in in a couple of things
actually but because I have had so many
deep interests in so many different
topics and I've really really pursued
them very seriously throughout my life
even
during times when people used to make
fun of me for that what's the point of
knowing all these things yeah what's the
point of knowing all this information
people used to make fun of me yeah I
still did it I didn't care what people
thought
um so you have to do that if you really
want to go in that direction, whatever
topics you find interesting, study them
in depth. You can't study things
shallowly. You to study everything in
depth. So, you have to spend time
becoming becoming specialist in one
thing at a time and then retain that
information and do it in in multiple
areas and topics. It's not for
everybody. It's very hard. Most people
will find it super painful.
And then you have to find ways of
making, you know, turning some of that
knowledge or some of the skills into
something that's actually monetizable.
So you have to find your own way in
that.
I never went out with the objective that
I want to be a polyath or whatever. I
was just following my curiosity my
entire life and that's what brought me
to wherever I am today. Critical return
says how can I stop procrastinating and
increase focus?
How do you stop? So, you cut off all the
things that make you procrastinate.
Destroy them. Let's say on your phone
you have 20 apps that make you
procrastinate. Delete the goddamn apps.
H
let's say you have five friends who are
wasters of your time.
End those friendships.
See, very easy to say, very hard to do.
Do it. It'll work out. That's all.
VSVS says um why UFOs have not evolved
like fighter jets in terms of shape and
size. They've always been circular since
their inception. Even today they're
mostly circular in shape. Who has seen
UFOs? The UFOs only appear in the US. My
my hunch is that these UFOs, they are
secret US technology.
And if you see the UFOs that that
appeared last year all across the United
States, they were in all kinds of
different shapes and sizes,
some of them were like orbs, some of
them were in other shapes. So it's not
just like circular or sort of saucer
saucer shaped. You have all kinds of
differently shaped UFOs that you see
these days, but only in the US
apparently. [laughter]
Okay. So most likely these are secret
technological programs of the US
military.
VSB says, "Please tell what you think
about the latest Muhammad Salahha's
situation."
Who is Muhammad Salha?
I don't know Muhammad. Are you talking
about Mo Salah, the Egyptian origin
footballer? What's the situation? I I
don't know. I If it is Muhammad Salah, I
don't know who that is. If it is
Muhammad Salah, the Egyptian footballer,
I don't know what the situation is. I'm
not keeping track of football so I have
no idea.
No idea. Sorry.
VSVS says is an operation or strike like
operation zur could be done by India in
this month? Very unlikely.
Very unlikely.
Okay. Dur Kamat says our Rahul is
against the Vedas being the central
authority of the civilization. I don't
think you concur with him on that.
The rigeda is the foundational text of
Indian civilization. It's the oldest
literature on the planet and the other
vedas came from that.
So the foundational literature, the
foundational texts, the foundational
heart and soul of our civilization is
the Vedas. That's how I see it. If
somebody disagrees with with me, that's
their choice.
Okay. Real says Poland is making huge
progress despite EU downfall. Who says
there is an EU downfall of Poland? Why
China, Vietnam, Japanese eta people are
more disciplined despite being worse
than us, having worse than us?
Poland is making huge progress. Poland
is being propped up as the next European
military superpower
to defend Europe, Western Europe against
Russia. That's why the US, etc., NATO
are bulking up the Polish military and
that obviously is going to have a good
financial effect on Poland. There's no
EU downfall of Poland. No such there is
an EU EU downfall of Poland. I'm not
I've not seen any EU downfall. There are
some disagreements about immigration
etc. Beyond that everything is fine,
right? So Poland is doing good because
Poland is next in line. Look at the
geography. Look at the map. I don't open
it now. If you look at the map, you will
say that after Belaros you have po in
Ukraine you have Poland. So Poland has
to stand in the way next in case Russia
decides to go west. Which is why Poland
is very important. UMX glowhaha says are
you vegetarian? How does it matter? How
does it matter? What difference does it
make if I'm vegetarian or not?
Ask me good questions. Yeah. UMX says
thoughts on book never finished by David
Gogggins.
I have not read any any of his books.
I'm aware of his famous book. what um uh
can't hurt me or something like that. I
haven't read it. I don't read self-help
books. Not read any self-help book in
dec like like two decades almost.
[clears throat]
So I I don't know. Okay. Vsvs says what
is the history of the broka tribe? I
don't know.
I don't know.
There are all kinds of small little
ethnic groups etc. tribes clans in
India. How will I know the history of
each of them? I don't know the history
of the broka tribe. I read newspaper
that white women visiting the dakli
region where brokpa tribe live for
having arian kids. I have no idea about
this. No idea.
Vsvs says what's the mystery of food
fighters during second world war? It's
not food fighters it is foo fighters. Fu
fighters. These were UFO sightings.
Flying saucers they were called. So you
had American fighter planes flying
around in the continental United States.
if I'm not mistaken. And they saw these
flying saucers and they they called them
foo fighters and they would try to
pursue them, but these things would just
outrun them, outmaneuver them like it's
like it was a joke. So that's why they
were called Foo Fighters. And then you
had
a music band, rock band or pop band
called the Foo Fighters. You want to see
this? Okay, let's quickly take a look at
this.
Foo Fighters. Okay, let's do this. Foo
Fighters,
rock band, but original
uh UFOs,
Foo Fighters, uh mysterious Foo
Fighters. See, like, yeah, that sort of
thing. So, pilot was scared shitless
apparently and so on. All right. All
right. Um
let's please stop taking super chats
now. It's almost 4 hours now. It's not
healthy for me to do this so long.
So I request you all to please stop
taking super but no you won't listen.
You won't listen.
Okay I'm I'm ending this in like five
minutes. Rahul says I was saying my
dharma predates any book. In order for a
book to write about my dharma my dharma
must have predated that book and few
insecure people turn it into my
character assassination. Look Rahul you
can decide and determine what your
dharma is. That is 100% the right of
every Hindu. That is what differentiates
Hinduism from everything else. There is
no book. If you don't want to follow a
book, you want to see things from a
different perspective, you have the
right to do that. And no one can stop
you. And that is also part of our
dharma. That's why you had so many
different philosophical branches of
dharma including both dharma, jina
dharma and so much more. Even Charvaka
which is completely materialistic and
atheistic. So it's entirely up to you.
Nobody has the right to tell you what is
right, what's wrong and whether you are
on the right path or wrong path. You
determine what is your path. I see it in
a specific way. You don't have to agree
with me and I have no right to say that
you are wrong. You are on your path. I
am on my path and that's how it is.
Wouldn't the world be a better place if
everybody saw it like this? Yeah. Okay.
Vs vs says Aush Singh says how to stop
this conversions. How to redermatize the
regions like the Far East. Please look
none of us can stop the conversions. The
government of India has to ban
conversions and stop the inflow of money
from abroad.
That's what has to happen. What will we
individuals do? You try to do something,
they'll throw us in jail. The government
of India will throw us in jail. The
government is to enact laws, make
conversions illegal. If somebody wants
to convert on their own, make it legal.
But if somebody is coming here with the
purpose of converting Indians by
lecturing them and brainwashing them,
that has to be illegal. That has to be a
jailable offense and stop the inflow of
these billions of dollars every year
coming in from god knows where. These
things have to happen. And then
obviously we can take steps to reivilize
everybody else, everybody who has been
affected by this. That will take time.
But first stop the conversions, the
industrial scale mass conversions. Why
is the government of India not seeing
this as a threat? I just don't get it.
That's about it. vs Jashi Ram sir Jashi
Ram thank you very much and that brings
us to the end of today's live chat VSBs
let's end this now I'm ending it now
that's the last one thank you very much
everybody it was fun it was long it was
fun I enjoyed it thank you everybody for
trusting me
trusting me to answer your questions
obviously I won't be able to answer all
the questions but thank you so much
anyway I've tried my best and I'll keep
trying my best. All right, thank you so
much. It's almost 4 hours, but it was
fun. I look forward to seeing you next
week in next week's live streams.
Please, please keep learning things.
Please keep asking your questions.
That's the only way to learn and keep
raising your standards. I'll see you
very soon in the next next live stream.
Take care everyone. Bye-bye.